[
  {
    "question": "<strong>How do Prokaryotic cell differ from eukaryotic cell? [AI 99] ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Nucleus</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>Devoid of nuclear membrane</span></strong><span>and nucleolus&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>No deoxyribonucleoproteins i.e. their nucleic DNA is not associated with basic protein (histone).&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>The genome consists of a single molecule double stranded DNA arranged in the form of a circle.</span></li> \n <li><span>Mitotic division does not occur and these divide by binary fission.</span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>Cytoplasm&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>No protoplasmic streaming&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Absence of endoplasmic reticulum Mitochondria, lysosomes and golgi apparatus.&nbsp;</span></strong></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>Chemical composition&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cell wall of prokaryotes contain Muramic acid and peptidoglycan (no sterols) while cell wall of eukaryotes contains sterols.</span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the composition of cell membrane? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>The plasma membrane is about 40% lipid and&nbsp;<strong><u>60%</u>&nbsp;protein</strong>, [AIIMS 94] but these proportions vary greatly. Most of the lipids in the plasma membrane are phospholipids.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the intracellular organelles that have double membrane. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Nucleus&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Endoplasmic membrane&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Mitochondria</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which cell organelle has extrachromosomal DNA? [IOM 08] ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Mitochondria</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are heterochromatin and euchromatin? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Heterochromatin – highly condensed chromatin fibres that are transcriptionally inactive, 10% chromatin is heterochromatin. &nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Euchromatin – more extended form of DNA that is&nbsp;<strong>transcriptionally active</strong>, [IOM 09] 90% chromatin is euchromatin.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the main function of the nucleolus? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>It is responsible for rRNA synthesis by assembling the ribosomes</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the cells that have more than one nucleus. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Hepatocytes –binucleate&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Osteoclasts - &nbsp;multinucleate&nbsp;</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are polysomes? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Polyribosomes (or polysomes) are a cluster of ribosomes, bound to a mRNA molecule. &nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Many ribosomes read one mRNA simultaneously, progressing along the mRNA to synthesize the same protein.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Circulatory system in a cell is name for: [IOM 08] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) RER</span></li> \n<li><span>B) SER&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Golgi apparatus&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Polyribosome</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: A) RER</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>The transport system of a cell is comprised of: [KU 13] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ol> \n <li><span>Endoplasmic reticulum</span></li> \n <li><span>Ribosome</span></li> \n <li><span>Nucleus</span></li> \n <li><span>Mitochondria</span></li> \n</ol>   \n<p><strong><span>Ans: A) Endoplasmic reticulum</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the functions of Smooth endoplasmic reticulum? [BPKIHS 08] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>Steroid Hormones synthesis</span></strong><span>[UP 95]&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Hydroxylation reactions&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Conjugation reaction&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Glycogen metabolism&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>In striated muscles, for storage of calcium ions, as sarcoplasmic reticulum.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the function of Golgi apparatus? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The proteins that are synthesized by rough endoplasmic reticulum must next be sent to the Golgi apparatus. [BPKIHS 12]</span></li> \n <li><span>Newly synthesized proteins enter into the Cis-Golgi, <strong><u>sorting</u>and the glycosylation of proteins</strong>&nbsp;[AI 08,14] occur in medial golgi and Packaging occurs in Trans-golgi for secretion as secretory vesicles. &nbsp;</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span><br></span> <span><br></span></p> \n<p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which of the following is the marker of Golgi apparatus? [AI 95, IOM 11] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Pyruvate kinase&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Adenylate cyclase&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Sodium potassium ATPase</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Galactosyl transferase&nbsp;</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Galactosyl transferase</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Galactosyl transferase is a type of glycosyltransferase which catalyzes the transfer of galactose. It occurs in golgi apparatus as a part of post-translational modification.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is Hyperproinsulinemia? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Elevated level of proinsulin in the serum resulting from failure of a peptidase to cleave proinsulin and C-peptide in the Golgi apparatus, resulting in NIDDM.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How are lysosomes produced? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>The synthesis of lysosomal hydrolase occurs in the RER, the hydrolases are transferred to the Golgi apparatus, where they are modified and packaged into lysosomes.</span></p> \n<p><span>They are produced by budding from the trans side of golgi apparatus.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are peroxisomes? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>They are specialized type of lysosomes in a way that they contain various enzymes involved in various stages of degradation.</span></li> \n <li><span>The major product they degrade is hydrogen peroxide and the major enzyme thus is catalase.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the functions of peroxisomes. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Degradation of hydrogen peroxide</span></li> \n <li><span>Beta-oxidation of very long fatty acids</span></li> \n <li><span>Bile acid and cholesterol synthesis</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is Zellweger syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Zellweger syndrome, also called cerebrohepatorenal syndrome, is a rare congenital disorder, characterized by the reduction or absence of functional peroxisomes in the cells of an individual.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are the enzymes required for electron transport system located in mitochondria? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>In the <strong>infolding of inner membrane of mitochondria called as cristae</strong>. [BPKIHS08]<strong> ",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name cytoskeletal elements. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Microfilaments - smallest</span></li> \n <li><span>Intermediate filaments</span></li> \n <li><span>Microtubules – largest</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the function of microfilaments? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cellular motility for cells like WBC</span></li> \n <li><span>Form contractile ring in cytokinesis</span></li> \n <li><span>Form core of microvilli and thus increase the absorption area of epithelial cells.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name intermediate filaments. ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Keratin&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; –&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Desmin</span></p> \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Vimentin&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Peripherin</span></p> \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Internexin&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Neurofilament</span></p> \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Lamins&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Nestin</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Functions of microtubules are: ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Intracellular transport of vesicles</span></li> \n <li><span>In cilia and flagella -&nbsp;<strong>responsible for shape and motility of the cell</strong>. [AI 95]&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Microtubules form mitotic spindles.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Cell motility is due to: [AIIMS 96] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Fibrin B)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Phorin</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Tubulin D)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Flagellin</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: C) Tubulin</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Tubulin is a protein present in microtubules of cells and responsible for cell motility.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are stereocilia? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>They are apical modification of cell; closely related to cilia or microvilli.</span></li> \n <li><span>But they are taller and branched unlike microvilli and do not have the motility like cilia.</span></li> \n <li><span>Some consider them specialized microvilli.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are stereocilia found? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Branched – epididymis</span></li> \n <li><span>Unbranched – hair cells in inner ear</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong> What is the ATP splitting enzyme in cilia? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Dynein is a very large&nbsp;<strong>force generating protein</strong>&nbsp;[AI 01] that has a molecular configuration similar to arms. Contraction of these arms facilitates the movement of cilia and flagella of bacteria.</span></p> \n<p><span>Kinesin also has similar activity.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong> Name disease conditions due to accumulation of intermediate filaments. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Alzheimer’s disease</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Mallory bodies</span></strong><span>in Alcoholic hepatitis. [UP 93, AP 94]</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the drugs that prevent formation of mitotic spindle. ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Vinblastine and Vincristine – thus used in cancer therapy</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the components of basement membrane? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Collagen type IV</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Laminin</span></strong><span>[AI 92, 95]&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Fibronectin&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Entactin&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Proteoglycans</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is difference between basement membrane and basal lamina? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The basement membrane is the fusion of two lamina, the basal lamina and the reticular lamina (or lamina reticularis).</span></li> \n <li><span>The basal lamina is a layer of extracellular matrix secreted by the epithelial cells, on which the epithelium sits and a reticular lamina secreted by other cells.</span></li> \n <li><span>The term \"basal lamina\" is usually used with electron microscopy, while the term \"basement membrane\" is usually used with light microscopy.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are desmosomes and hemidesmosomes? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>A desmosome (desmos, band or dense, soma, body), also known as macula adherens (plural</span></strong><span>: maculae adherentes) is a cell structure for cell-to-cell adhesion.</span></li> \n <li><span>Desmosomes help to resist shearing forces and are found in simple and stratified squamous epithelium.</span></li> \n <li><span>Hemidesmosome are half of desmosome and help to bind the epithelial cell with the basement membrane of the cell.&nbsp;</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are cadherins? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cadherins are calcium dependent adhesion proteins that ensure the adhesion of cells within the tissues.</span></li> \n <li><span>First step of invasion of malignant cells through an epithelium results from a loss of expression of cadherins that weakens the epithelium.</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span>[@<strong><u>Ca</u></strong> <strong><u>d</u></strong> <strong><u>herins</u></strong> - <strong><u>Ca</u></strong> <strong><u>d</u></strong>ependent ad<strong><u>herin</u></strong> molecule]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Catabolism of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is carried out by [IOM 10] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Lysosomes</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Mitochondria</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Endoplasmic reticulum&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Peroxisomes</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Peroxisomes</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n <li><strong><span> subchpstart::::TISSUESsubchpend::::</span></strong></li> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are stratified cuboidal epithelium found? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Duct of salivary gland and sweat gland. It is the only place where we find the stratified cuboidal epithelium.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where&nbsp;are transitional epithelium found? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Transitional epithelium occurs in ureters, urinary bladder and&nbsp;<strong>proximal (prostatic) urethra</strong>. [IOM 10]</span></li> \n <li><span>Within the cytoplasm are fusiform vesicles lined by unit membranes, the inner lamellae of are similarly thickened.</span></li> \n <li><span>These vesicles are probably formed by infolding of the plasma membrane, and their walls constitute<strong>reserve material</strong>&nbsp;[AI 03] used in rapid expansion of the cells.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the composition of extracellular matrix? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Gel part contain proteoglycan (heparin sulphate +&nbsp;chondroitin sulphate)&nbsp;and glycoprotein. <strong>The major macromolecules primarily found in extracellular matrix are <u></u> </strong>[AI 14]</span></li> \n <li><span>Fibrillar protein contains collagen, elastin, Fibrillin (elastin + Fibrillin =elastic fibres) and fibronectin.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>All are glycoproteins except: [IOM 10] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) hCG&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Immunoglobulins&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) ALP</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Albumin</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Albumin</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is collagen? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Collagen is the major macromolecule of connective tissue and is the most common protein in the animal world.</span></li> \n <li><span>The most important property of collagen molecule is&nbsp;<strong>triple helix structure</strong>[AIIMS 95, UP 99] made of three polypeptide subunits.</span></li> \n <li><span>Collagen consists of&nbsp;<strong>glycine, <u>proline</u></strong> and 4-hydroxyproline. [UP 00]</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the steps in synthesis of collagen? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Collagen precursors are produced in rough endoplasmic reticulum of fibroblasts </span><span>?</span><span> hydroxylation that requires vitamin C and glycosylation in golgi apparatus </span><span>?</span><span> triple helix formation&nbsp;in golgi apparatus </span><span>?</span><span> released from golgi as procollagen </span><span>?</span><span> propeptides are removed forming tropocollagen </span><span>?</span><span> tropocollagen are assembled to form collagen fibre.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the defect in Ehlers Danlos syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Conversion of procollagen to tropocollagen is defective.</span></li> \n <li><span>Forms fragile skin, hyperextensible joints, varicose veins.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the types of collagen? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Collagen</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Features</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type I</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Strongest; Present in strong tissues like b<strong><u>ONE</u></strong>s, ligaments, tendon, skin, sclera, teeth, mature scar </span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type II</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Weaker; Present in <strong>cartilages</strong></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\"> (car<strong><u>TWO</u></strong>lage), [IOM 02] intervertebral disc</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type III</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Much weaker; Present in Blood vessels, forms reticular fibres in various organs; Stained with PAS and silver salts&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type IV</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Weakest of all collagens</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Supports only a row of epithelial cells as in<strong> basement membrane </strong></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[IOM 09]</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[Note: Collagenase (metalloenzyme containing zinc) breaks type III collagen in granulation tissue to replace by type I collagen(stronger)]</span></p>\r\n<ol start=\"9\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 115%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which enzyme mediates the degradation of basement membrane? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Basement membrane consists of network of amorphous non-fibrillar collagen (mostly type IV).</span></p> \n<p><strong><span>Matrix metalloproteinases</span></strong><span>&nbsp;[AI 07] is a family of enzymes that are involved in degradation of basement membrane.</span></p> \n<p><span>[Note: Type IV collagenase is present in neutrophil and malignant cell - so have similar mechanism of invading the basement membrane for chemotaxis and metastases respectively]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which collagen is defective in Alport syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Type IV collagen</span></p> \n<p><span>Alport syndrome is due to mutation of COL4A3, COL4A4, COL4A5 gene involved in collagen biosynthesis, which leads to poor&nbsp;type IV collagen&nbsp;network, which is an important structural component of basement membranes in the&nbsp;kidney, inner&nbsp;ear and&nbsp;eye.</span></p> \n<p><span>It causes glomerulonephritis, hearing loss, cataract, keratoconus, lenticonus, etc.</span></p> \n<p><span>[<strong><u>@ Alports syndrome</u> -<u> &nbsp;Al-four-t’s Syndrome - type IV</u></strong>]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are elastic fibres located? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>These fibres provide elasticity or resilience to the tissues meaning that they will return to their resting length after stretch.</span></li> \n <li><span>They are present in lungs, blood vessels especially arteries and dermis of the skin. </span></li> \n <li><span>Elastin + Fibrillin =elastin fibres</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the defect in Marfan syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Marfan’s Syndrome is associated with a gene defect in <strong>Fibrillin-1 protein</strong> [AI 14] located in chromosome 15, that causes significant weakening in elastic tissue. </span></p> \n<p><span>[@<strong>M</strong>ar<strong>F</strong>a<strong>N</strong>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<strong>M</strong>utation&nbsp;<strong>F</strong>ibrilli<strong>N</strong>,&nbsp;<strong>F</strong>iftee<strong>N</strong>]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the features of Marfan's syndrome? [AI 94, AIIMS 95] ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"321\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Musculoskeletal signs and conditions -&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Long, thin extremities (arachnodactyly)</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Tall body habitus&nbsp;</span></strong></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Pectus deformity&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">High arched palate</span></strong></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Hyperextensible joints and ligaments</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"321\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ocular signs and conditions -&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Reduced vision as the result of&nbsp;<strong>subluxation of lens (ectopic lentis) </strong>[AI 93]&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Myopia&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Glaucoma&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Retinal detachment</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"321\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Cardiovascular signs and conditions&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Aortic aneurysm that typically begin at the&nbsp;<strong><u>base of aorta</u></strong>&nbsp;[AI 95]&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Aortic regurgitation&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Mitral valve prolapse&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">SABE</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr style=\"height: 36.4pt;\">\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt; height: 36.4pt;\" width=\"321\">&nbsp;</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ol start=\"15\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Normal metacarpal index is: ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) &gt;10.4 B) 5.4-7.9</span></li> \n<li><span>C) &gt;5.4 D) 8.4-10.4</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: B) 5.4-7.9</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Metacarpal index(MCI) is determined by dividing the length of each of the last four metacarpals by the width of its midpoint and averaging the values.</span></p> \n<p><strong><span>Normal MCI &lt;8</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Those with Marfan's syndrome have MCI &gt;8.4</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are examples of Glycosaminoglycan? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Glycosaminoglycan contains two glucose molecules (disaccharide) along with amino group, thus the name glycosaminoglycan.</span></p> \n<p><span>GAG is either sulphated or non-sulphated.</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>Sulphated GAG</span></strong><span>: Chondroitin sulphate, Heparin sulphate, Dermatan sulphate and Keratin sulphate</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Non sulphated include</span></strong><span>: Hyaluronic acid</span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>Presence of sulphate makes the GAG negatively charged and thus repels negatively charged particles.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are Hyaluronic acids? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Hyaluronic acids are <strong>non-sulphated</strong> GAGs that form extracellular matrix.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are proteoglycans? &nbsp;[AI 07] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Proteoglycans are macromolecules in which a core<strong>protein is attached covalently to one or more glycosaminoglycan chains (complex carbohydrate</strong>).</span></li> \n <li><span>They are sulphated GAGs.</span></li> \n <li><span>They are <strong>chondroitin sulphate</strong>, heparin sulphate, dermatan sulphate and keratin sulphate.</span></li> \n <li><span>Proteoglycans&nbsp;<strong>hold&nbsp;<u>large</u>amount of water and occupy space</strong>. They are&nbsp;<strong>negatively charged</strong>.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Why are proteins not filtered in Glomerulosa? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Proteins are negatively charged and the basement membranes of podocytes contain heparin sulphate that is negatively charged and thus they repel protein.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the types of cartilages? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: .2in; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: .75in; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"72\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Hyaline</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">cartilage</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 178.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"237\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Contains maximum amount of glycosaminoglycan. </span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Location - Articular surface of synovial joints, cartilage of nose, larynx, trachea, bronchi</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: .75in; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"72\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Elastic</span></strong></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">cartilage</span></strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 178.0pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"237\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Contains maximum elastic fibers</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Location - External ear, <strong>epiglottis</strong> [UP 95, 98]</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[@<strong><u><span style=\"background: #CCCCCC;\">E</span></u></strong><span style=\"background: #CCCCCC;\">lastic cartilage: Ext.&nbsp;<strong><u>e</u></strong>ar, <strong><u>E</u></strong>piglottis]</span>&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: .75in; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"72\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Fibro-</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">cartilage</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 178.0pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"237\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Lacks perichondrium</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">This is the only cartilage that has type I collagen. Presence of type I collagen gives cartilage greater resistance being stretched.</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Location - intervertebral disc, menisci of knee</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ol start=\"21\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are hard and soft keratin? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 45.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"60\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Hard </span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">keratin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 196.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"261\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">These keratins are less pliable than soft keratins as&nbsp;<strong>they contain more disulfide bonds</strong>. [AI 12] E.g. hair, horn,&nbsp;<strong>nail&nbsp;</strong></span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 45.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"60\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Soft </span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">keratin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 196.0pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"261\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">These keratins are more pliable than hard keratins as they contain less number of disulfide bonds. E.g.&nbsp;<strong>skin</strong>&nbsp;(and callus).</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ol start=\"22\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are labile cells? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Labile cells are the cells that continue to proliferate throughout the life, replacing the cells that are continually being destroyed. Labile cells in body are&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cells of splenic, lymphoid and hematopoietic tissue&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Cells of surface epithelium such as stratified squamous surfaces of skin, oral cavity, cervix, vagina</span></li> \n <li><span>Lining mucosa of all the excretory ducts of glands of the body such as salivary glands, pancreas, and biliary tract</span></li> \n <li><span>The columnar epithelium of GI tract, uterus, fallopian tube and transitional epithelium of the urinary tract</span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which of the following cells are not labile? [AI 93, IOM 00] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Intestinal cells&nbsp; B) Keratinocytes&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Kupffer cells&nbsp; D) Hepatocytes</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Hepatocytes</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>The cells of liver, pancreas, kidney are [NAMS12] ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -24.55pt; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: 120.5pt 141.75pt; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 42.55pt;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">A) Stable cells B) &nbsp;&nbsp; Permanent cells</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -24.55pt; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: 120.5pt 141.75pt; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 42.55pt;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">C) Labile cells D)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; None &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: right; text-indent: -24.55pt; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: 120.5pt 141.75pt; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 42.55pt;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ans: A) Stable cells </span></strong></p>\r\n<ol start=\"25\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Define epimysium, perimysium and endomysium. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Epi – connective tissue that surrounds entire muscle</span></li> \n <li><span>Peri – connective tissue that surrounds bundle of muscle fibres</span></li> \n <li><span>Endo – connective tissue that surrounds each muscle fibre</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are differences between Type I and Type II muscles? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: .2in; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Features</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type I (slow twitch muscle)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type II&nbsp;(fast twitch muscle)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Function</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Postural, weight bearing</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Purposeful movements</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Energy source</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">fatty acids</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Glycogen</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Mitochondria</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Many (aerobic respiration- oxidative)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Few (anaerobic respiration)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Color</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Red, more myoglobin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">White, less myoglobin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Fatigue</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Slow</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Rapid</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: #E5E5E5; border: none; padding: 0in; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[@ Type <strong><u>1</u></strong>: &lsquo;1 <strong><u>slow fat red ox&rsquo;</u></strong>: &ndash;slow twitch &ndash;lipid accumulation &ndash;red fibers &ndash;oxidative</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: #E5E5E5; border: none; padding: 0in; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type <strong><u>2</u></strong>: &lsquo;<strong><u>2 fast skinny white breasts</u></strong>&rsquo;: &ndash;fast twitch &ndash;low lipid &ndash; white fibers, like chicken breasts]</span></p>\r\n<ol start=\"27\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are Nissl Bodies? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Nissl bodies are rough endoplasmic reticulum of nerve cell. </span></p> \n<p><span>They are called as Nissl body because they are stained with Nissl stain</span></p> \n<ol> \n <li><strong><span> subchpstart::::EMBRYOLOGYsubchpend::::</span></strong></li> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>When are the 2 layer and 3 layer embryos formed? ",
    "answer": " </strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>2-layer embryo in 2<sup>nd</sup> week&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>3-layer embryo in 3<sup>rd</sup> week</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span>[@ 2 week – 2 layer, 3 weeks – 3 layer, 4 weeks – 4 limbs appear] </span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Somites develop from ......... mesoderm. [PGI 99] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Paraxial B) Lateral plate&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Extraembryonic&nbsp; D) Intermediate&nbsp; </span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: A) Paraxial</span></strong></p> \n<p><span><br></span> <span><br></span></p> \n<p><span>During the course of development, the paraxial mesoderm becomes segmented into cubical masses which are known as somites or metamere or primitive segments.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Muscular component of dorsal aorta develops from: [AI 11] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Intermediate mesoderm</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Axial mesoderm</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Lateral plate mesoderm</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Paraxial mesoderm</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Paraxial mesoderm</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Paraxial mesoderm &gt; Lateral plate mesoderm<br>Vascular smooth muscle cells are traditionally believed to arise from splanchnic layer of lateral plate mesoderm. But recent studies have demonstrated that smooth muscle cells of dorsal aorta are actually derived from&nbsp;<strong>paraxial somatic mesoderm</strong>.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are primordial germ cells? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>The primordial germ cells origin from the wall of yolk sac that is endodermal. They&nbsp;migrate into the gonadal portion of urogenital ridge. So, all the components are mesodermal in origin but the germ cells are endodermal in origin.</span></p> \n<p><span>Genital and urological structures develop from urogenital ridge located in the posterior wall of embryo abdomen. </span></p> \n<p><span>Role of primordial germ cells – As the germ cells reach the gonadal portion of urogenital ridge, they form gamete in the future. They induce the mesoderm to develop into the gonad. &nbsp;Thus, although the mesodermal cells are destined to develop into gonad, they cannot differentiate into gonad if not induced by primordial germ cells.&nbsp;</span></p> \n<p><span>In the Y chromosome, there is SRY (Sex determining Region of Y) gene,&nbsp;and this gene codes for Testis Determining Factor (TDF). In the presence of TDF, that gonad becomes the testis, and in absence of TDF, it becomes the ovary. In other words, the embryo is preprogrammed to become a female, and if there is no stimulus, it will become female.&nbsp;A female is not female because she has XX chromosome, she is female because she does not have Y chromosome.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the factors that make male organs in a preprogrammed female gonad? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 18.9pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 99.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"132\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Testis determining factor</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 125.35pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"167\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">From SRY gene of y chromosome makes testis.&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 99.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"132\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Testosterone secreted from Leydig cells</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 125.35pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"167\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Forms duct system of male reproductive system.</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 99.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"132\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Mullerian Inhibiting factor (MIF) from Sertoli cells</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 125.35pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"167\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">That inhibits the mullerian tract.</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ul>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">The inhibition is compulsory. If there is no inhibition, the preprogrammed embryo forms all female organs.&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">In absence of SRY gene, there is no production of TDF. Testis does not develop and there is no production of testosterone to produce male organs. There are no&nbsp;Sertoli cells to produce MIF, female organs develop as preprogrammed.&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n</ul>\r\n<ol start=\"6\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Development of testes is dependent upon which of the following? [MANIPAL 02] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) X chromosome</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Y chromosome</span></li> \n<li><span>C) XY chromosome</span></li> \n<li><span>D) XX chromosome</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: B) Y chromosome</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>The gene that regulates normal morphogenesis during development is: [AIIMS 02] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) PTEN</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Homeobox</span></li> \n<li><span>C) P-16</span></li> \n<li><span>D) FMR-1 GENE</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: B) Homeobox</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Researchers believe that the development of an embryo is greatly influenced by so called homeotic genes, which interact with networks of other genes to determine the position of various body parts.</span></p> \n<p><span>Homeotic genes contain sequences called&nbsp;<strong>homeo-boxes</strong>, which can be found in organisms ranging from sea urchins to humans.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What Hormones are required to form female organs and male organs? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which phase of intrauterine life has the highest risk of teratogenicity? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The fetus has the highest risk of teratogenicity in post conception age of 3-8 weeks. Before this time (&lt;2 weeks), the fetus is either intact or dead. After this period (9<sup>+</sup>weeks), there is either hypertrophy or hyperplasia.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is embryonal period and fetal period? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Embryonal period – 3-8 weeks [KU 13]</span></li> \n <li><span>Fetal period – 8weeks to child birth</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which cell in the body is tetraploid? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Primary spermatocyte or oocyte is tetraploid.</span></li> \n <li><span>After DNA replication, DNA amount is doubled to form tetraploid cells.</span></li> \n <li><span>Though there are still 46 chromosomes, each chromosome has twice much DNA after DNA replication, so the cell is tetraploid.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How many sperm and ovum does the primary spermatocyte and primary oocyte give? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>One Primary oocyte gives one ovum. There is unequal first meiotic cell division of primary oocyte. One cell receives almost all cytoplasm, and the other cell thus converts into first polar body, same for secondary oocyte. Thus, only one ovum is produced. One Primary spermatocyte gives 4 sperms.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the difference in mitosis division in other somatic cells and Zygote? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>In somatic cells, there is cell growth in between the cell division. When a cell divides, it results in half the size of mother cell. The daughter cell grows to a definite size before it again divides.</span></li> \n <li><span>In zygote, there is no growth of the daughter cells. There is only the division of the cell. So, when a zygote divides into two cells, each cell is half the size of zygote, and when these cells further divide, to form 4 and 8 cells, the size of the resulting cells become 1/4<sup>th</sup> and 1/8<sup>th</sup> the size of the zygote. Thus there is no increase in volume. <strong>The zygote and morula are of same size</strong>. This type of cell division is also called as Cleavage division. As the cleavage proceeds, a solid mass of&nbsp;<strong><u>sixteen cell</u></strong>[UP 94] is formed. This is called Morula.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is blastocyst? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Blastocyst consists of an outer layer or trophoblast and inner layer of embryoblast. The enclosed cavity is blastocele.</span></li> \n <li><strong><u><span>Blastocyst</span></u></strong><strong><span>is the stage of implantation in the endometrium of uterus</span></strong><span> [AI 94] consisting of two cell groups.</span> \n  <ol> \n   <li><span>Embryoblast</span></li> \n   <li><span>Trophoblast</span></li> \n  </ol> </li> \n</ul>   \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the types of trophoblast? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Cytotrophoblast</span></p> \n<p><span>Syncytiotrophoblast </span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cells of cytotrophoblast are metabolically active and divide rapidly; the divided cells fuse and form syncytiotrophoblast.</span></li> \n <li><span>Syncytiotrophoblast cause erosion of uterus for implantation and produce hCG hormone. </span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>When does uteroplacental circulation begin? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>On day 11-12</span></strong><span>, [IOM 11, KU 13] primitive uteroplacental circulation forms with oxygenated maternal blood arriving via spiral arterioles, seeping into the lacunae and leaving via endometrial venous capillaries.</span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the events in second week of embryo? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Formation of early placenta</span></p> \n<p><span>Formation of double layered embryo</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Epiblast – give future embryo</span></li> \n <li><span>Hypoblast – degenerate</span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>The cell layers between epiblast and hypoblast are separable except at a point called as prechordal plate. It is the site of future mouth. It determines the polarity of the circular disc of cells that has no polarity. By determining the head end, we can now determine the left, right, head and tail end of embryo.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is primitive groove or streak? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Towards the tail end of epiblast forms a groove in the midline, called primitive streak. Here, the cells of the epiblast from left and right migrates to the midline and goes beneath to the hypoblast.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How are endoderm, mesoderm, and ectoderm formed? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The cells from the epiblast migrate down through the primitive streak to the site of hypoblast. The cells of hypoblast degenerate and are replaced by the migrated cells to form endoderm.</span></li> \n <li><span>The cells of epiblast that migrate and remain in the position between epiblast and hypoblast form middle layer. The cells that migrate either in left or right side to form mesoderm.</span></li> \n <li><span>The remaining cells in epiblast form ectoderm.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How is Notochord formed? ",
    "answer": " </strong>  \n<ul> \n <li><span>The cells from the epiblast that migrate through primitive streak and remain between epiblast and hypoblast in the left and right form middle layer. The cells at the site of middle layer that remain in the midline form Notochord.&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Notochord gives Nucleus pulposus of intervertebral disc. </span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the sub-divisions of ectoderm? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Neuroectoderm – occupy midline</span></li> \n <li><span>Neural crest ectoderm – occupy side of neuroectoderm cells</span></li> \n <li><span>Surface ectoderm</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is gastroschisis? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Defect in fusion of the lateral body folds results in gastroschisis – abdominal viscera exit through a defect in the abdominal wall and are in the amniotic cavity.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which of these appears first? [IOM 09] ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">A) Pharyngeal arch</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">B) Lower limb bud&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">C) Upper limb bud&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">D) Neural plate</span></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: right; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ans: D) Neural plate</span></strong></p>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">1 week</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Fertilized oocyte, Pronucleus</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">2 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Implantation</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">3 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Gastrulation, notochordal process</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">4 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Somite number 4-12, neural fold fuses&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">5 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Somite number 30, leg buds, lens placode, pharyngeal arches,&nbsp;<strong>ossification of clavicle starts.</strong>&nbsp;[IOM 08]&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">6 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Foot plate&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">7 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ossification commences&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">8 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Upper limbs longer and bent at elbow.</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 20.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: Wingdings;\">&micro;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 40.0pt 0in 20.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "BASIC ANATOMY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How do Prokaryotic cell differ from eukaryotic cell? [AI 99] ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Nucleus</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>Devoid of nuclear membrane</span></strong><span>and nucleolus&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>No deoxyribonucleoproteins i.e. their nucleic DNA is not associated with basic protein (histone).&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>The genome consists of a single molecule double stranded DNA arranged in the form of a circle.</span></li> \n <li><span>Mitotic division does not occur and these divide by binary fission.</span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>Cytoplasm&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>No protoplasmic streaming&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Absence of endoplasmic reticulum Mitochondria, lysosomes and golgi apparatus.&nbsp;</span></strong></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>Chemical composition&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cell wall of prokaryotes contain Muramic acid and peptidoglycan (no sterols) while cell wall of eukaryotes contains sterols.</span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the composition of cell membrane? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>The plasma membrane is about 40% lipid and&nbsp;<strong><u>60%</u>&nbsp;protein</strong>, [AIIMS 94] but these proportions vary greatly. Most of the lipids in the plasma membrane are phospholipids.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the intracellular organelles that have double membrane. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Nucleus&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Endoplasmic membrane&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Mitochondria</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which cell organelle has extrachromosomal DNA? [IOM 08] ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Mitochondria</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are heterochromatin and euchromatin? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Heterochromatin – highly condensed chromatin fibres that are transcriptionally inactive, 10% chromatin is heterochromatin. &nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Euchromatin – more extended form of DNA that is&nbsp;<strong>transcriptionally active</strong>, [IOM 09] 90% chromatin is euchromatin.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the main function of the nucleolus? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>It is responsible for rRNA synthesis by assembling the ribosomes</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the cells that have more than one nucleus. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Hepatocytes –binucleate&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Osteoclasts - &nbsp;multinucleate&nbsp;</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are polysomes? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Polyribosomes (or polysomes) are a cluster of ribosomes, bound to a mRNA molecule. &nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Many ribosomes read one mRNA simultaneously, progressing along the mRNA to synthesize the same protein.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Circulatory system in a cell is name for: [IOM 08] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) RER</span></li> \n<li><span>B) SER&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Golgi apparatus&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Polyribosome</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: A) RER</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>The transport system of a cell is comprised of: [KU 13] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ol> \n <li><span>Endoplasmic reticulum</span></li> \n <li><span>Ribosome</span></li> \n <li><span>Nucleus</span></li> \n <li><span>Mitochondria</span></li> \n</ol>   \n<p><strong><span>Ans: A) Endoplasmic reticulum</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the functions of Smooth endoplasmic reticulum? [BPKIHS 08] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>Steroid Hormones synthesis</span></strong><span>[UP 95]&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Hydroxylation reactions&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Conjugation reaction&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Glycogen metabolism&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>In striated muscles, for storage of calcium ions, as sarcoplasmic reticulum.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the function of Golgi apparatus? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The proteins that are synthesized by rough endoplasmic reticulum must next be sent to the Golgi apparatus. [BPKIHS 12]</span></li> \n <li><span>Newly synthesized proteins enter into the Cis-Golgi, <strong><u>sorting</u>and the glycosylation of proteins</strong>&nbsp;[AI 08,14] occur in medial golgi and Packaging occurs in Trans-golgi for secretion as secretory vesicles. &nbsp;</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span><br></span> <span><br></span></p> \n<p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which of the following is the marker of Golgi apparatus? [AI 95, IOM 11] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Pyruvate kinase&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Adenylate cyclase&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Sodium potassium ATPase</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Galactosyl transferase&nbsp;</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Galactosyl transferase</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Galactosyl transferase is a type of glycosyltransferase which catalyzes the transfer of galactose. It occurs in golgi apparatus as a part of post-translational modification.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is Hyperproinsulinemia? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Elevated level of proinsulin in the serum resulting from failure of a peptidase to cleave proinsulin and C-peptide in the Golgi apparatus, resulting in NIDDM.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How are lysosomes produced? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>The synthesis of lysosomal hydrolase occurs in the RER, the hydrolases are transferred to the Golgi apparatus, where they are modified and packaged into lysosomes.</span></p> \n<p><span>They are produced by budding from the trans side of golgi apparatus.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are peroxisomes? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>They are specialized type of lysosomes in a way that they contain various enzymes involved in various stages of degradation.</span></li> \n <li><span>The major product they degrade is hydrogen peroxide and the major enzyme thus is catalase.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the functions of peroxisomes. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Degradation of hydrogen peroxide</span></li> \n <li><span>Beta-oxidation of very long fatty acids</span></li> \n <li><span>Bile acid and cholesterol synthesis</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is Zellweger syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Zellweger syndrome, also called cerebrohepatorenal syndrome, is a rare congenital disorder, characterized by the reduction or absence of functional peroxisomes in the cells of an individual.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are the enzymes required for electron transport system located in mitochondria? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>In the <strong>infolding of inner membrane of mitochondria called as cristae</strong>. [BPKIHS08]<strong> ",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name cytoskeletal elements. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Microfilaments - smallest</span></li> \n <li><span>Intermediate filaments</span></li> \n <li><span>Microtubules – largest</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the function of microfilaments? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cellular motility for cells like WBC</span></li> \n <li><span>Form contractile ring in cytokinesis</span></li> \n <li><span>Form core of microvilli and thus increase the absorption area of epithelial cells.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name intermediate filaments. ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Keratin&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; –&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Desmin</span></p> \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Vimentin&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Peripherin</span></p> \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Internexin&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Neurofilament</span></p> \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Lamins&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Nestin</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Functions of microtubules are: ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Intracellular transport of vesicles</span></li> \n <li><span>In cilia and flagella -&nbsp;<strong>responsible for shape and motility of the cell</strong>. [AI 95]&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Microtubules form mitotic spindles.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Cell motility is due to: [AIIMS 96] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Fibrin B)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Phorin</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Tubulin D)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Flagellin</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: C) Tubulin</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Tubulin is a protein present in microtubules of cells and responsible for cell motility.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are stereocilia? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>They are apical modification of cell; closely related to cilia or microvilli.</span></li> \n <li><span>But they are taller and branched unlike microvilli and do not have the motility like cilia.</span></li> \n <li><span>Some consider them specialized microvilli.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are stereocilia found? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Branched – epididymis</span></li> \n <li><span>Unbranched – hair cells in inner ear</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong> What is the ATP splitting enzyme in cilia? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Dynein is a very large&nbsp;<strong>force generating protein</strong>&nbsp;[AI 01] that has a molecular configuration similar to arms. Contraction of these arms facilitates the movement of cilia and flagella of bacteria.</span></p> \n<p><span>Kinesin also has similar activity.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong> Name disease conditions due to accumulation of intermediate filaments. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Alzheimer’s disease</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Mallory bodies</span></strong><span>in Alcoholic hepatitis. [UP 93, AP 94]</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the drugs that prevent formation of mitotic spindle. ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Vinblastine and Vincristine – thus used in cancer therapy</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the components of basement membrane? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Collagen type IV</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Laminin</span></strong><span>[AI 92, 95]&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Fibronectin&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Entactin&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Proteoglycans</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is difference between basement membrane and basal lamina? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The basement membrane is the fusion of two lamina, the basal lamina and the reticular lamina (or lamina reticularis).</span></li> \n <li><span>The basal lamina is a layer of extracellular matrix secreted by the epithelial cells, on which the epithelium sits and a reticular lamina secreted by other cells.</span></li> \n <li><span>The term \"basal lamina\" is usually used with electron microscopy, while the term \"basement membrane\" is usually used with light microscopy.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are desmosomes and hemidesmosomes? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>A desmosome (desmos, band or dense, soma, body), also known as macula adherens (plural</span></strong><span>: maculae adherentes) is a cell structure for cell-to-cell adhesion.</span></li> \n <li><span>Desmosomes help to resist shearing forces and are found in simple and stratified squamous epithelium.</span></li> \n <li><span>Hemidesmosome are half of desmosome and help to bind the epithelial cell with the basement membrane of the cell.&nbsp;</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are cadherins? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cadherins are calcium dependent adhesion proteins that ensure the adhesion of cells within the tissues.</span></li> \n <li><span>First step of invasion of malignant cells through an epithelium results from a loss of expression of cadherins that weakens the epithelium.</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span>[@<strong><u>Ca</u></strong> <strong><u>d</u></strong> <strong><u>herins</u></strong> - <strong><u>Ca</u></strong> <strong><u>d</u></strong>ependent ad<strong><u>herin</u></strong> molecule]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Catabolism of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is carried out by [IOM 10] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Lysosomes</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Mitochondria</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Endoplasmic reticulum&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Peroxisomes</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Peroxisomes</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n <li><strong><span> subchpstart::::TISSUESsubchpend::::</span></strong></li> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are stratified cuboidal epithelium found? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Duct of salivary gland and sweat gland. It is the only place where we find the stratified cuboidal epithelium.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where&nbsp;are transitional epithelium found? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Transitional epithelium occurs in ureters, urinary bladder and&nbsp;<strong>proximal (prostatic) urethra</strong>. [IOM 10]</span></li> \n <li><span>Within the cytoplasm are fusiform vesicles lined by unit membranes, the inner lamellae of are similarly thickened.</span></li> \n <li><span>These vesicles are probably formed by infolding of the plasma membrane, and their walls constitute<strong>reserve material</strong>&nbsp;[AI 03] used in rapid expansion of the cells.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the composition of extracellular matrix? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Gel part contain proteoglycan (heparin sulphate +&nbsp;chondroitin sulphate)&nbsp;and glycoprotein. <strong>The major macromolecules primarily found in extracellular matrix are <u></u> </strong>[AI 14]</span></li> \n <li><span>Fibrillar protein contains collagen, elastin, Fibrillin (elastin + Fibrillin =elastic fibres) and fibronectin.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>All are glycoproteins except: [IOM 10] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) hCG&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Immunoglobulins&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) ALP</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Albumin</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Albumin</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is collagen? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Collagen is the major macromolecule of connective tissue and is the most common protein in the animal world.</span></li> \n <li><span>The most important property of collagen molecule is&nbsp;<strong>triple helix structure</strong>[AIIMS 95, UP 99] made of three polypeptide subunits.</span></li> \n <li><span>Collagen consists of&nbsp;<strong>glycine, <u>proline</u></strong> and 4-hydroxyproline. [UP 00]</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the steps in synthesis of collagen? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Collagen precursors are produced in rough endoplasmic reticulum of fibroblasts </span><span>?</span><span> hydroxylation that requires vitamin C and glycosylation in golgi apparatus </span><span>?</span><span> triple helix formation&nbsp;in golgi apparatus </span><span>?</span><span> released from golgi as procollagen </span><span>?</span><span> propeptides are removed forming tropocollagen </span><span>?</span><span> tropocollagen are assembled to form collagen fibre.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the defect in Ehlers Danlos syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Conversion of procollagen to tropocollagen is defective.</span></li> \n <li><span>Forms fragile skin, hyperextensible joints, varicose veins.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the types of collagen? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Collagen</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Features</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type I</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Strongest; Present in strong tissues like b<strong><u>ONE</u></strong>s, ligaments, tendon, skin, sclera, teeth, mature scar </span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type II</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Weaker; Present in <strong>cartilages</strong></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\"> (car<strong><u>TWO</u></strong>lage), [IOM 02] intervertebral disc</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type III</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Much weaker; Present in Blood vessels, forms reticular fibres in various organs; Stained with PAS and silver salts&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type IV</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Weakest of all collagens</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Supports only a row of epithelial cells as in<strong> basement membrane </strong></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[IOM 09]</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[Note: Collagenase (metalloenzyme containing zinc) breaks type III collagen in granulation tissue to replace by type I collagen(stronger)]</span></p>\r\n<ol start=\"9\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 115%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which enzyme mediates the degradation of basement membrane? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Basement membrane consists of network of amorphous non-fibrillar collagen (mostly type IV).</span></p> \n<p><strong><span>Matrix metalloproteinases</span></strong><span>&nbsp;[AI 07] is a family of enzymes that are involved in degradation of basement membrane.</span></p> \n<p><span>[Note: Type IV collagenase is present in neutrophil and malignant cell - so have similar mechanism of invading the basement membrane for chemotaxis and metastases respectively]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which collagen is defective in Alport syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Type IV collagen</span></p> \n<p><span>Alport syndrome is due to mutation of COL4A3, COL4A4, COL4A5 gene involved in collagen biosynthesis, which leads to poor&nbsp;type IV collagen&nbsp;network, which is an important structural component of basement membranes in the&nbsp;kidney, inner&nbsp;ear and&nbsp;eye.</span></p> \n<p><span>It causes glomerulonephritis, hearing loss, cataract, keratoconus, lenticonus, etc.</span></p> \n<p><span>[<strong><u>@ Alports syndrome</u> -<u> &nbsp;Al-four-t’s Syndrome - type IV</u></strong>]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are elastic fibres located? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>These fibres provide elasticity or resilience to the tissues meaning that they will return to their resting length after stretch.</span></li> \n <li><span>They are present in lungs, blood vessels especially arteries and dermis of the skin. </span></li> \n <li><span>Elastin + Fibrillin =elastin fibres</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the defect in Marfan syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Marfan’s Syndrome is associated with a gene defect in <strong>Fibrillin-1 protein</strong> [AI 14] located in chromosome 15, that causes significant weakening in elastic tissue. </span></p> \n<p><span>[@<strong>M</strong>ar<strong>F</strong>a<strong>N</strong>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<strong>M</strong>utation&nbsp;<strong>F</strong>ibrilli<strong>N</strong>,&nbsp;<strong>F</strong>iftee<strong>N</strong>]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the features of Marfan's syndrome? [AI 94, AIIMS 95] ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"321\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Musculoskeletal signs and conditions -&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Long, thin extremities (arachnodactyly)</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Tall body habitus&nbsp;</span></strong></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Pectus deformity&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">High arched palate</span></strong></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Hyperextensible joints and ligaments</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"321\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ocular signs and conditions -&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Reduced vision as the result of&nbsp;<strong>subluxation of lens (ectopic lentis) </strong>[AI 93]&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Myopia&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Glaucoma&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Retinal detachment</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"321\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Cardiovascular signs and conditions&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Aortic aneurysm that typically begin at the&nbsp;<strong><u>base of aorta</u></strong>&nbsp;[AI 95]&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Aortic regurgitation&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Mitral valve prolapse&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">SABE</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr style=\"height: 36.4pt;\">\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt; height: 36.4pt;\" width=\"321\">&nbsp;</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ol start=\"15\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Normal metacarpal index is: ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) &gt;10.4 B) 5.4-7.9</span></li> \n<li><span>C) &gt;5.4 D) 8.4-10.4</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: B) 5.4-7.9</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Metacarpal index(MCI) is determined by dividing the length of each of the last four metacarpals by the width of its midpoint and averaging the values.</span></p> \n<p><strong><span>Normal MCI &lt;8</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Those with Marfan's syndrome have MCI &gt;8.4</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are examples of Glycosaminoglycan? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Glycosaminoglycan contains two glucose molecules (disaccharide) along with amino group, thus the name glycosaminoglycan.</span></p> \n<p><span>GAG is either sulphated or non-sulphated.</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>Sulphated GAG</span></strong><span>: Chondroitin sulphate, Heparin sulphate, Dermatan sulphate and Keratin sulphate</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Non sulphated include</span></strong><span>: Hyaluronic acid</span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>Presence of sulphate makes the GAG negatively charged and thus repels negatively charged particles.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are Hyaluronic acids? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Hyaluronic acids are <strong>non-sulphated</strong> GAGs that form extracellular matrix.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are proteoglycans? &nbsp;[AI 07] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Proteoglycans are macromolecules in which a core<strong>protein is attached covalently to one or more glycosaminoglycan chains (complex carbohydrate</strong>).</span></li> \n <li><span>They are sulphated GAGs.</span></li> \n <li><span>They are <strong>chondroitin sulphate</strong>, heparin sulphate, dermatan sulphate and keratin sulphate.</span></li> \n <li><span>Proteoglycans&nbsp;<strong>hold&nbsp;<u>large</u>amount of water and occupy space</strong>. They are&nbsp;<strong>negatively charged</strong>.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Why are proteins not filtered in Glomerulosa? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Proteins are negatively charged and the basement membranes of podocytes contain heparin sulphate that is negatively charged and thus they repel protein.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the types of cartilages? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: .2in; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: .75in; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"72\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Hyaline</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">cartilage</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 178.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"237\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Contains maximum amount of glycosaminoglycan. </span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Location - Articular surface of synovial joints, cartilage of nose, larynx, trachea, bronchi</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: .75in; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"72\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Elastic</span></strong></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">cartilage</span></strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 178.0pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"237\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Contains maximum elastic fibers</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Location - External ear, <strong>epiglottis</strong> [UP 95, 98]</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[@<strong><u><span style=\"background: #CCCCCC;\">E</span></u></strong><span style=\"background: #CCCCCC;\">lastic cartilage: Ext.&nbsp;<strong><u>e</u></strong>ar, <strong><u>E</u></strong>piglottis]</span>&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: .75in; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"72\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Fibro-</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">cartilage</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 178.0pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"237\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Lacks perichondrium</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">This is the only cartilage that has type I collagen. Presence of type I collagen gives cartilage greater resistance being stretched.</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Location - intervertebral disc, menisci of knee</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ol start=\"21\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are hard and soft keratin? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 45.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"60\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Hard </span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">keratin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 196.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"261\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">These keratins are less pliable than soft keratins as&nbsp;<strong>they contain more disulfide bonds</strong>. [AI 12] E.g. hair, horn,&nbsp;<strong>nail&nbsp;</strong></span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 45.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"60\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Soft </span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">keratin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 196.0pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"261\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">These keratins are more pliable than hard keratins as they contain less number of disulfide bonds. E.g.&nbsp;<strong>skin</strong>&nbsp;(and callus).</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ol start=\"22\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are labile cells? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Labile cells are the cells that continue to proliferate throughout the life, replacing the cells that are continually being destroyed. Labile cells in body are&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cells of splenic, lymphoid and hematopoietic tissue&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Cells of surface epithelium such as stratified squamous surfaces of skin, oral cavity, cervix, vagina</span></li> \n <li><span>Lining mucosa of all the excretory ducts of glands of the body such as salivary glands, pancreas, and biliary tract</span></li> \n <li><span>The columnar epithelium of GI tract, uterus, fallopian tube and transitional epithelium of the urinary tract</span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which of the following cells are not labile? [AI 93, IOM 00] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Intestinal cells&nbsp; B) Keratinocytes&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Kupffer cells&nbsp; D) Hepatocytes</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Hepatocytes</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>The cells of liver, pancreas, kidney are [NAMS12] ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -24.55pt; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: 120.5pt 141.75pt; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 42.55pt;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">A) Stable cells B) &nbsp;&nbsp; Permanent cells</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -24.55pt; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: 120.5pt 141.75pt; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 42.55pt;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">C) Labile cells D)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; None &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: right; text-indent: -24.55pt; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: 120.5pt 141.75pt; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 42.55pt;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ans: A) Stable cells </span></strong></p>\r\n<ol start=\"25\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Define epimysium, perimysium and endomysium. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Epi – connective tissue that surrounds entire muscle</span></li> \n <li><span>Peri – connective tissue that surrounds bundle of muscle fibres</span></li> \n <li><span>Endo – connective tissue that surrounds each muscle fibre</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are differences between Type I and Type II muscles? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: .2in; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Features</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type I (slow twitch muscle)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type II&nbsp;(fast twitch muscle)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Function</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Postural, weight bearing</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Purposeful movements</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Energy source</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">fatty acids</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Glycogen</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Mitochondria</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Many (aerobic respiration- oxidative)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Few (anaerobic respiration)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Color</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Red, more myoglobin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">White, less myoglobin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Fatigue</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Slow</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Rapid</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: #E5E5E5; border: none; padding: 0in; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[@ Type <strong><u>1</u></strong>: &lsquo;1 <strong><u>slow fat red ox&rsquo;</u></strong>: &ndash;slow twitch &ndash;lipid accumulation &ndash;red fibers &ndash;oxidative</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: #E5E5E5; border: none; padding: 0in; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type <strong><u>2</u></strong>: &lsquo;<strong><u>2 fast skinny white breasts</u></strong>&rsquo;: &ndash;fast twitch &ndash;low lipid &ndash; white fibers, like chicken breasts]</span></p>\r\n<ol start=\"27\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are Nissl Bodies? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Nissl bodies are rough endoplasmic reticulum of nerve cell. </span></p> \n<p><span>They are called as Nissl body because they are stained with Nissl stain</span></p> \n<ol> \n <li><strong><span> subchpstart::::EMBRYOLOGYsubchpend::::</span></strong></li> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>When are the 2 layer and 3 layer embryos formed? ",
    "answer": " </strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>2-layer embryo in 2<sup>nd</sup> week&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>3-layer embryo in 3<sup>rd</sup> week</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span>[@ 2 week – 2 layer, 3 weeks – 3 layer, 4 weeks – 4 limbs appear] </span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Somites develop from ......... mesoderm. [PGI 99] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Paraxial B) Lateral plate&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Extraembryonic&nbsp; D) Intermediate&nbsp; </span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: A) Paraxial</span></strong></p> \n<p><span><br></span> <span><br></span></p> \n<p><span>During the course of development, the paraxial mesoderm becomes segmented into cubical masses which are known as somites or metamere or primitive segments.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Muscular component of dorsal aorta develops from: [AI 11] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Intermediate mesoderm</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Axial mesoderm</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Lateral plate mesoderm</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Paraxial mesoderm</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Paraxial mesoderm</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Paraxial mesoderm &gt; Lateral plate mesoderm<br>Vascular smooth muscle cells are traditionally believed to arise from splanchnic layer of lateral plate mesoderm. But recent studies have demonstrated that smooth muscle cells of dorsal aorta are actually derived from&nbsp;<strong>paraxial somatic mesoderm</strong>.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are primordial germ cells? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>The primordial germ cells origin from the wall of yolk sac that is endodermal. They&nbsp;migrate into the gonadal portion of urogenital ridge. So, all the components are mesodermal in origin but the germ cells are endodermal in origin.</span></p> \n<p><span>Genital and urological structures develop from urogenital ridge located in the posterior wall of embryo abdomen. </span></p> \n<p><span>Role of primordial germ cells – As the germ cells reach the gonadal portion of urogenital ridge, they form gamete in the future. They induce the mesoderm to develop into the gonad. &nbsp;Thus, although the mesodermal cells are destined to develop into gonad, they cannot differentiate into gonad if not induced by primordial germ cells.&nbsp;</span></p> \n<p><span>In the Y chromosome, there is SRY (Sex determining Region of Y) gene,&nbsp;and this gene codes for Testis Determining Factor (TDF). In the presence of TDF, that gonad becomes the testis, and in absence of TDF, it becomes the ovary. In other words, the embryo is preprogrammed to become a female, and if there is no stimulus, it will become female.&nbsp;A female is not female because she has XX chromosome, she is female because she does not have Y chromosome.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the factors that make male organs in a preprogrammed female gonad? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 18.9pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 99.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"132\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Testis determining factor</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 125.35pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"167\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">From SRY gene of y chromosome makes testis.&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 99.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"132\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Testosterone secreted from Leydig cells</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 125.35pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"167\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Forms duct system of male reproductive system.</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 99.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"132\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Mullerian Inhibiting factor (MIF) from Sertoli cells</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 125.35pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"167\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">That inhibits the mullerian tract.</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ul>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">The inhibition is compulsory. If there is no inhibition, the preprogrammed embryo forms all female organs.&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">In absence of SRY gene, there is no production of TDF. Testis does not develop and there is no production of testosterone to produce male organs. There are no&nbsp;Sertoli cells to produce MIF, female organs develop as preprogrammed.&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n</ul>\r\n<ol start=\"6\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Development of testes is dependent upon which of the following? [MANIPAL 02] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) X chromosome</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Y chromosome</span></li> \n<li><span>C) XY chromosome</span></li> \n<li><span>D) XX chromosome</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: B) Y chromosome</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>The gene that regulates normal morphogenesis during development is: [AIIMS 02] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) PTEN</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Homeobox</span></li> \n<li><span>C) P-16</span></li> \n<li><span>D) FMR-1 GENE</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: B) Homeobox</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Researchers believe that the development of an embryo is greatly influenced by so called homeotic genes, which interact with networks of other genes to determine the position of various body parts.</span></p> \n<p><span>Homeotic genes contain sequences called&nbsp;<strong>homeo-boxes</strong>, which can be found in organisms ranging from sea urchins to humans.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What Hormones are required to form female organs and male organs? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which phase of intrauterine life has the highest risk of teratogenicity? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The fetus has the highest risk of teratogenicity in post conception age of 3-8 weeks. Before this time (&lt;2 weeks), the fetus is either intact or dead. After this period (9<sup>+</sup>weeks), there is either hypertrophy or hyperplasia.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is embryonal period and fetal period? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Embryonal period – 3-8 weeks [KU 13]</span></li> \n <li><span>Fetal period – 8weeks to child birth</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which cell in the body is tetraploid? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Primary spermatocyte or oocyte is tetraploid.</span></li> \n <li><span>After DNA replication, DNA amount is doubled to form tetraploid cells.</span></li> \n <li><span>Though there are still 46 chromosomes, each chromosome has twice much DNA after DNA replication, so the cell is tetraploid.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How many sperm and ovum does the primary spermatocyte and primary oocyte give? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>One Primary oocyte gives one ovum. There is unequal first meiotic cell division of primary oocyte. One cell receives almost all cytoplasm, and the other cell thus converts into first polar body, same for secondary oocyte. Thus, only one ovum is produced. One Primary spermatocyte gives 4 sperms.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the difference in mitosis division in other somatic cells and Zygote? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>In somatic cells, there is cell growth in between the cell division. When a cell divides, it results in half the size of mother cell. The daughter cell grows to a definite size before it again divides.</span></li> \n <li><span>In zygote, there is no growth of the daughter cells. There is only the division of the cell. So, when a zygote divides into two cells, each cell is half the size of zygote, and when these cells further divide, to form 4 and 8 cells, the size of the resulting cells become 1/4<sup>th</sup> and 1/8<sup>th</sup> the size of the zygote. Thus there is no increase in volume. <strong>The zygote and morula are of same size</strong>. This type of cell division is also called as Cleavage division. As the cleavage proceeds, a solid mass of&nbsp;<strong><u>sixteen cell</u></strong>[UP 94] is formed. This is called Morula.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is blastocyst? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Blastocyst consists of an outer layer or trophoblast and inner layer of embryoblast. The enclosed cavity is blastocele.</span></li> \n <li><strong><u><span>Blastocyst</span></u></strong><strong><span>is the stage of implantation in the endometrium of uterus</span></strong><span> [AI 94] consisting of two cell groups.</span> \n  <ol> \n   <li><span>Embryoblast</span></li> \n   <li><span>Trophoblast</span></li> \n  </ol> </li> \n</ul>   \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the types of trophoblast? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Cytotrophoblast</span></p> \n<p><span>Syncytiotrophoblast </span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cells of cytotrophoblast are metabolically active and divide rapidly; the divided cells fuse and form syncytiotrophoblast.</span></li> \n <li><span>Syncytiotrophoblast cause erosion of uterus for implantation and produce hCG hormone. </span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>When does uteroplacental circulation begin? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>On day 11-12</span></strong><span>, [IOM 11, KU 13] primitive uteroplacental circulation forms with oxygenated maternal blood arriving via spiral arterioles, seeping into the lacunae and leaving via endometrial venous capillaries.</span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the events in second week of embryo? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Formation of early placenta</span></p> \n<p><span>Formation of double layered embryo</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Epiblast – give future embryo</span></li> \n <li><span>Hypoblast – degenerate</span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>The cell layers between epiblast and hypoblast are separable except at a point called as prechordal plate. It is the site of future mouth. It determines the polarity of the circular disc of cells that has no polarity. By determining the head end, we can now determine the left, right, head and tail end of embryo.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is primitive groove or streak? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Towards the tail end of epiblast forms a groove in the midline, called primitive streak. Here, the cells of the epiblast from left and right migrates to the midline and goes beneath to the hypoblast.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How are endoderm, mesoderm, and ectoderm formed? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The cells from the epiblast migrate down through the primitive streak to the site of hypoblast. The cells of hypoblast degenerate and are replaced by the migrated cells to form endoderm.</span></li> \n <li><span>The cells of epiblast that migrate and remain in the position between epiblast and hypoblast form middle layer. The cells that migrate either in left or right side to form mesoderm.</span></li> \n <li><span>The remaining cells in epiblast form ectoderm.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How is Notochord formed? ",
    "answer": " </strong>  \n<ul> \n <li><span>The cells from the epiblast that migrate through primitive streak and remain between epiblast and hypoblast in the left and right form middle layer. The cells at the site of middle layer that remain in the midline form Notochord.&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Notochord gives Nucleus pulposus of intervertebral disc. </span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the sub-divisions of ectoderm? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Neuroectoderm – occupy midline</span></li> \n <li><span>Neural crest ectoderm – occupy side of neuroectoderm cells</span></li> \n <li><span>Surface ectoderm</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is gastroschisis? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Defect in fusion of the lateral body folds results in gastroschisis – abdominal viscera exit through a defect in the abdominal wall and are in the amniotic cavity.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which of these appears first? [IOM 09] ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">A) Pharyngeal arch</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">B) Lower limb bud&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">C) Upper limb bud&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">D) Neural plate</span></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: right; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ans: D) Neural plate</span></strong></p>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">1 week</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Fertilized oocyte, Pronucleus</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">2 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Implantation</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">3 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Gastrulation, notochordal process</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">4 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Somite number 4-12, neural fold fuses&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">5 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Somite number 30, leg buds, lens placode, pharyngeal arches,&nbsp;<strong>ossification of clavicle starts.</strong>&nbsp;[IOM 08]&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">6 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Foot plate&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">7 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ossification commences&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">8 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Upper limbs longer and bent at elbow.</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 20.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: Wingdings;\">&micro;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 40.0pt 0in 20.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "CELL ORGANELLES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How do Prokaryotic cell differ from eukaryotic cell? [AI 99] ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Nucleus</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>Devoid of nuclear membrane</span></strong><span>and nucleolus&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>No deoxyribonucleoproteins i.e. their nucleic DNA is not associated with basic protein (histone).&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>The genome consists of a single molecule double stranded DNA arranged in the form of a circle.</span></li> \n <li><span>Mitotic division does not occur and these divide by binary fission.</span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>Cytoplasm&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>No protoplasmic streaming&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Absence of endoplasmic reticulum Mitochondria, lysosomes and golgi apparatus.&nbsp;</span></strong></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>Chemical composition&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cell wall of prokaryotes contain Muramic acid and peptidoglycan (no sterols) while cell wall of eukaryotes contains sterols.</span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the composition of cell membrane? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>The plasma membrane is about 40% lipid and&nbsp;<strong><u>60%</u>&nbsp;protein</strong>, [AIIMS 94] but these proportions vary greatly. Most of the lipids in the plasma membrane are phospholipids.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the intracellular organelles that have double membrane. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Nucleus&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Endoplasmic membrane&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Mitochondria</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which cell organelle has extrachromosomal DNA? [IOM 08] ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Mitochondria</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are heterochromatin and euchromatin? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Heterochromatin – highly condensed chromatin fibres that are transcriptionally inactive, 10% chromatin is heterochromatin. &nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Euchromatin – more extended form of DNA that is&nbsp;<strong>transcriptionally active</strong>, [IOM 09] 90% chromatin is euchromatin.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the main function of the nucleolus? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>It is responsible for rRNA synthesis by assembling the ribosomes</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the cells that have more than one nucleus. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Hepatocytes –binucleate&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Osteoclasts - &nbsp;multinucleate&nbsp;</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are polysomes? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Polyribosomes (or polysomes) are a cluster of ribosomes, bound to a mRNA molecule. &nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Many ribosomes read one mRNA simultaneously, progressing along the mRNA to synthesize the same protein.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Circulatory system in a cell is name for: [IOM 08] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) RER</span></li> \n<li><span>B) SER&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Golgi apparatus&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Polyribosome</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: A) RER</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>The transport system of a cell is comprised of: [KU 13] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ol> \n <li><span>Endoplasmic reticulum</span></li> \n <li><span>Ribosome</span></li> \n <li><span>Nucleus</span></li> \n <li><span>Mitochondria</span></li> \n</ol>   \n<p><strong><span>Ans: A) Endoplasmic reticulum</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the functions of Smooth endoplasmic reticulum? [BPKIHS 08] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>Steroid Hormones synthesis</span></strong><span>[UP 95]&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Hydroxylation reactions&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Conjugation reaction&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Glycogen metabolism&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>In striated muscles, for storage of calcium ions, as sarcoplasmic reticulum.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the function of Golgi apparatus? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The proteins that are synthesized by rough endoplasmic reticulum must next be sent to the Golgi apparatus. [BPKIHS 12]</span></li> \n <li><span>Newly synthesized proteins enter into the Cis-Golgi, <strong><u>sorting</u>and the glycosylation of proteins</strong>&nbsp;[AI 08,14] occur in medial golgi and Packaging occurs in Trans-golgi for secretion as secretory vesicles. &nbsp;</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span><br></span> <span><br></span></p> \n<p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which of the following is the marker of Golgi apparatus? [AI 95, IOM 11] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Pyruvate kinase&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Adenylate cyclase&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Sodium potassium ATPase</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Galactosyl transferase&nbsp;</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Galactosyl transferase</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Galactosyl transferase is a type of glycosyltransferase which catalyzes the transfer of galactose. It occurs in golgi apparatus as a part of post-translational modification.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is Hyperproinsulinemia? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Elevated level of proinsulin in the serum resulting from failure of a peptidase to cleave proinsulin and C-peptide in the Golgi apparatus, resulting in NIDDM.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How are lysosomes produced? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>The synthesis of lysosomal hydrolase occurs in the RER, the hydrolases are transferred to the Golgi apparatus, where they are modified and packaged into lysosomes.</span></p> \n<p><span>They are produced by budding from the trans side of golgi apparatus.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are peroxisomes? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>They are specialized type of lysosomes in a way that they contain various enzymes involved in various stages of degradation.</span></li> \n <li><span>The major product they degrade is hydrogen peroxide and the major enzyme thus is catalase.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the functions of peroxisomes. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Degradation of hydrogen peroxide</span></li> \n <li><span>Beta-oxidation of very long fatty acids</span></li> \n <li><span>Bile acid and cholesterol synthesis</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is Zellweger syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Zellweger syndrome, also called cerebrohepatorenal syndrome, is a rare congenital disorder, characterized by the reduction or absence of functional peroxisomes in the cells of an individual.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are the enzymes required for electron transport system located in mitochondria? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>In the <strong>infolding of inner membrane of mitochondria called as cristae</strong>. [BPKIHS08]<strong> ",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name cytoskeletal elements. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Microfilaments - smallest</span></li> \n <li><span>Intermediate filaments</span></li> \n <li><span>Microtubules – largest</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the function of microfilaments? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cellular motility for cells like WBC</span></li> \n <li><span>Form contractile ring in cytokinesis</span></li> \n <li><span>Form core of microvilli and thus increase the absorption area of epithelial cells.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name intermediate filaments. ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Keratin&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; –&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Desmin</span></p> \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Vimentin&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Peripherin</span></p> \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Internexin&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Neurofilament</span></p> \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Lamins&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Nestin</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Functions of microtubules are: ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Intracellular transport of vesicles</span></li> \n <li><span>In cilia and flagella -&nbsp;<strong>responsible for shape and motility of the cell</strong>. [AI 95]&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Microtubules form mitotic spindles.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Cell motility is due to: [AIIMS 96] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Fibrin B)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Phorin</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Tubulin D)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Flagellin</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: C) Tubulin</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Tubulin is a protein present in microtubules of cells and responsible for cell motility.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are stereocilia? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>They are apical modification of cell; closely related to cilia or microvilli.</span></li> \n <li><span>But they are taller and branched unlike microvilli and do not have the motility like cilia.</span></li> \n <li><span>Some consider them specialized microvilli.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are stereocilia found? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Branched – epididymis</span></li> \n <li><span>Unbranched – hair cells in inner ear</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong> What is the ATP splitting enzyme in cilia? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Dynein is a very large&nbsp;<strong>force generating protein</strong>&nbsp;[AI 01] that has a molecular configuration similar to arms. Contraction of these arms facilitates the movement of cilia and flagella of bacteria.</span></p> \n<p><span>Kinesin also has similar activity.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong> Name disease conditions due to accumulation of intermediate filaments. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Alzheimer’s disease</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Mallory bodies</span></strong><span>in Alcoholic hepatitis. [UP 93, AP 94]</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the drugs that prevent formation of mitotic spindle. ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Vinblastine and Vincristine – thus used in cancer therapy</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the components of basement membrane? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Collagen type IV</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Laminin</span></strong><span>[AI 92, 95]&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Fibronectin&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Entactin&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Proteoglycans</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is difference between basement membrane and basal lamina? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The basement membrane is the fusion of two lamina, the basal lamina and the reticular lamina (or lamina reticularis).</span></li> \n <li><span>The basal lamina is a layer of extracellular matrix secreted by the epithelial cells, on which the epithelium sits and a reticular lamina secreted by other cells.</span></li> \n <li><span>The term \"basal lamina\" is usually used with electron microscopy, while the term \"basement membrane\" is usually used with light microscopy.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are desmosomes and hemidesmosomes? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>A desmosome (desmos, band or dense, soma, body), also known as macula adherens (plural</span></strong><span>: maculae adherentes) is a cell structure for cell-to-cell adhesion.</span></li> \n <li><span>Desmosomes help to resist shearing forces and are found in simple and stratified squamous epithelium.</span></li> \n <li><span>Hemidesmosome are half of desmosome and help to bind the epithelial cell with the basement membrane of the cell.&nbsp;</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are cadherins? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cadherins are calcium dependent adhesion proteins that ensure the adhesion of cells within the tissues.</span></li> \n <li><span>First step of invasion of malignant cells through an epithelium results from a loss of expression of cadherins that weakens the epithelium.</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span>[@<strong><u>Ca</u></strong> <strong><u>d</u></strong> <strong><u>herins</u></strong> - <strong><u>Ca</u></strong> <strong><u>d</u></strong>ependent ad<strong><u>herin</u></strong> molecule]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Catabolism of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is carried out by [IOM 10] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Lysosomes</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Mitochondria</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Endoplasmic reticulum&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Peroxisomes</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Peroxisomes</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n <li><strong><span> subchpstart::::TISSUESsubchpend::::</span></strong></li> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are stratified cuboidal epithelium found? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Duct of salivary gland and sweat gland. It is the only place where we find the stratified cuboidal epithelium.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where&nbsp;are transitional epithelium found? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Transitional epithelium occurs in ureters, urinary bladder and&nbsp;<strong>proximal (prostatic) urethra</strong>. [IOM 10]</span></li> \n <li><span>Within the cytoplasm are fusiform vesicles lined by unit membranes, the inner lamellae of are similarly thickened.</span></li> \n <li><span>These vesicles are probably formed by infolding of the plasma membrane, and their walls constitute<strong>reserve material</strong>&nbsp;[AI 03] used in rapid expansion of the cells.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the composition of extracellular matrix? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Gel part contain proteoglycan (heparin sulphate +&nbsp;chondroitin sulphate)&nbsp;and glycoprotein. <strong>The major macromolecules primarily found in extracellular matrix are <u></u> </strong>[AI 14]</span></li> \n <li><span>Fibrillar protein contains collagen, elastin, Fibrillin (elastin + Fibrillin =elastic fibres) and fibronectin.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>All are glycoproteins except: [IOM 10] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) hCG&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Immunoglobulins&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) ALP</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Albumin</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Albumin</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is collagen? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Collagen is the major macromolecule of connective tissue and is the most common protein in the animal world.</span></li> \n <li><span>The most important property of collagen molecule is&nbsp;<strong>triple helix structure</strong>[AIIMS 95, UP 99] made of three polypeptide subunits.</span></li> \n <li><span>Collagen consists of&nbsp;<strong>glycine, <u>proline</u></strong> and 4-hydroxyproline. [UP 00]</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the steps in synthesis of collagen? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Collagen precursors are produced in rough endoplasmic reticulum of fibroblasts </span><span>?</span><span> hydroxylation that requires vitamin C and glycosylation in golgi apparatus </span><span>?</span><span> triple helix formation&nbsp;in golgi apparatus </span><span>?</span><span> released from golgi as procollagen </span><span>?</span><span> propeptides are removed forming tropocollagen </span><span>?</span><span> tropocollagen are assembled to form collagen fibre.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the defect in Ehlers Danlos syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Conversion of procollagen to tropocollagen is defective.</span></li> \n <li><span>Forms fragile skin, hyperextensible joints, varicose veins.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the types of collagen? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Collagen</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Features</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type I</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Strongest; Present in strong tissues like b<strong><u>ONE</u></strong>s, ligaments, tendon, skin, sclera, teeth, mature scar </span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type II</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Weaker; Present in <strong>cartilages</strong></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\"> (car<strong><u>TWO</u></strong>lage), [IOM 02] intervertebral disc</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type III</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Much weaker; Present in Blood vessels, forms reticular fibres in various organs; Stained with PAS and silver salts&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type IV</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Weakest of all collagens</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Supports only a row of epithelial cells as in<strong> basement membrane </strong></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[IOM 09]</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[Note: Collagenase (metalloenzyme containing zinc) breaks type III collagen in granulation tissue to replace by type I collagen(stronger)]</span></p>\r\n<ol start=\"9\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 115%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which enzyme mediates the degradation of basement membrane? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Basement membrane consists of network of amorphous non-fibrillar collagen (mostly type IV).</span></p> \n<p><strong><span>Matrix metalloproteinases</span></strong><span>&nbsp;[AI 07] is a family of enzymes that are involved in degradation of basement membrane.</span></p> \n<p><span>[Note: Type IV collagenase is present in neutrophil and malignant cell - so have similar mechanism of invading the basement membrane for chemotaxis and metastases respectively]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which collagen is defective in Alport syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Type IV collagen</span></p> \n<p><span>Alport syndrome is due to mutation of COL4A3, COL4A4, COL4A5 gene involved in collagen biosynthesis, which leads to poor&nbsp;type IV collagen&nbsp;network, which is an important structural component of basement membranes in the&nbsp;kidney, inner&nbsp;ear and&nbsp;eye.</span></p> \n<p><span>It causes glomerulonephritis, hearing loss, cataract, keratoconus, lenticonus, etc.</span></p> \n<p><span>[<strong><u>@ Alports syndrome</u> -<u> &nbsp;Al-four-t’s Syndrome - type IV</u></strong>]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are elastic fibres located? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>These fibres provide elasticity or resilience to the tissues meaning that they will return to their resting length after stretch.</span></li> \n <li><span>They are present in lungs, blood vessels especially arteries and dermis of the skin. </span></li> \n <li><span>Elastin + Fibrillin =elastin fibres</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the defect in Marfan syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Marfan’s Syndrome is associated with a gene defect in <strong>Fibrillin-1 protein</strong> [AI 14] located in chromosome 15, that causes significant weakening in elastic tissue. </span></p> \n<p><span>[@<strong>M</strong>ar<strong>F</strong>a<strong>N</strong>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<strong>M</strong>utation&nbsp;<strong>F</strong>ibrilli<strong>N</strong>,&nbsp;<strong>F</strong>iftee<strong>N</strong>]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the features of Marfan's syndrome? [AI 94, AIIMS 95] ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"321\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Musculoskeletal signs and conditions -&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Long, thin extremities (arachnodactyly)</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Tall body habitus&nbsp;</span></strong></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Pectus deformity&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">High arched palate</span></strong></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Hyperextensible joints and ligaments</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"321\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ocular signs and conditions -&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Reduced vision as the result of&nbsp;<strong>subluxation of lens (ectopic lentis) </strong>[AI 93]&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Myopia&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Glaucoma&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Retinal detachment</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"321\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Cardiovascular signs and conditions&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Aortic aneurysm that typically begin at the&nbsp;<strong><u>base of aorta</u></strong>&nbsp;[AI 95]&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Aortic regurgitation&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Mitral valve prolapse&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">SABE</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr style=\"height: 36.4pt;\">\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt; height: 36.4pt;\" width=\"321\">&nbsp;</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ol start=\"15\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Normal metacarpal index is: ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) &gt;10.4 B) 5.4-7.9</span></li> \n<li><span>C) &gt;5.4 D) 8.4-10.4</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: B) 5.4-7.9</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Metacarpal index(MCI) is determined by dividing the length of each of the last four metacarpals by the width of its midpoint and averaging the values.</span></p> \n<p><strong><span>Normal MCI &lt;8</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Those with Marfan's syndrome have MCI &gt;8.4</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are examples of Glycosaminoglycan? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Glycosaminoglycan contains two glucose molecules (disaccharide) along with amino group, thus the name glycosaminoglycan.</span></p> \n<p><span>GAG is either sulphated or non-sulphated.</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>Sulphated GAG</span></strong><span>: Chondroitin sulphate, Heparin sulphate, Dermatan sulphate and Keratin sulphate</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Non sulphated include</span></strong><span>: Hyaluronic acid</span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>Presence of sulphate makes the GAG negatively charged and thus repels negatively charged particles.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are Hyaluronic acids? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Hyaluronic acids are <strong>non-sulphated</strong> GAGs that form extracellular matrix.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are proteoglycans? &nbsp;[AI 07] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Proteoglycans are macromolecules in which a core<strong>protein is attached covalently to one or more glycosaminoglycan chains (complex carbohydrate</strong>).</span></li> \n <li><span>They are sulphated GAGs.</span></li> \n <li><span>They are <strong>chondroitin sulphate</strong>, heparin sulphate, dermatan sulphate and keratin sulphate.</span></li> \n <li><span>Proteoglycans&nbsp;<strong>hold&nbsp;<u>large</u>amount of water and occupy space</strong>. They are&nbsp;<strong>negatively charged</strong>.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Why are proteins not filtered in Glomerulosa? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Proteins are negatively charged and the basement membranes of podocytes contain heparin sulphate that is negatively charged and thus they repel protein.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the types of cartilages? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: .2in; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: .75in; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"72\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Hyaline</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">cartilage</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 178.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"237\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Contains maximum amount of glycosaminoglycan. </span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Location - Articular surface of synovial joints, cartilage of nose, larynx, trachea, bronchi</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: .75in; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"72\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Elastic</span></strong></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">cartilage</span></strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 178.0pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"237\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Contains maximum elastic fibers</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Location - External ear, <strong>epiglottis</strong> [UP 95, 98]</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[@<strong><u><span style=\"background: #CCCCCC;\">E</span></u></strong><span style=\"background: #CCCCCC;\">lastic cartilage: Ext.&nbsp;<strong><u>e</u></strong>ar, <strong><u>E</u></strong>piglottis]</span>&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: .75in; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"72\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Fibro-</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">cartilage</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 178.0pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"237\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Lacks perichondrium</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">This is the only cartilage that has type I collagen. Presence of type I collagen gives cartilage greater resistance being stretched.</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Location - intervertebral disc, menisci of knee</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ol start=\"21\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are hard and soft keratin? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 45.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"60\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Hard </span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">keratin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 196.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"261\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">These keratins are less pliable than soft keratins as&nbsp;<strong>they contain more disulfide bonds</strong>. [AI 12] E.g. hair, horn,&nbsp;<strong>nail&nbsp;</strong></span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 45.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"60\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Soft </span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">keratin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 196.0pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"261\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">These keratins are more pliable than hard keratins as they contain less number of disulfide bonds. E.g.&nbsp;<strong>skin</strong>&nbsp;(and callus).</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ol start=\"22\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are labile cells? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Labile cells are the cells that continue to proliferate throughout the life, replacing the cells that are continually being destroyed. Labile cells in body are&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cells of splenic, lymphoid and hematopoietic tissue&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Cells of surface epithelium such as stratified squamous surfaces of skin, oral cavity, cervix, vagina</span></li> \n <li><span>Lining mucosa of all the excretory ducts of glands of the body such as salivary glands, pancreas, and biliary tract</span></li> \n <li><span>The columnar epithelium of GI tract, uterus, fallopian tube and transitional epithelium of the urinary tract</span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which of the following cells are not labile? [AI 93, IOM 00] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Intestinal cells&nbsp; B) Keratinocytes&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Kupffer cells&nbsp; D) Hepatocytes</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Hepatocytes</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>The cells of liver, pancreas, kidney are [NAMS12] ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -24.55pt; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: 120.5pt 141.75pt; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 42.55pt;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">A) Stable cells B) &nbsp;&nbsp; Permanent cells</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -24.55pt; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: 120.5pt 141.75pt; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 42.55pt;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">C) Labile cells D)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; None &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: right; text-indent: -24.55pt; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: 120.5pt 141.75pt; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 42.55pt;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ans: A) Stable cells </span></strong></p>\r\n<ol start=\"25\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Define epimysium, perimysium and endomysium. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Epi – connective tissue that surrounds entire muscle</span></li> \n <li><span>Peri – connective tissue that surrounds bundle of muscle fibres</span></li> \n <li><span>Endo – connective tissue that surrounds each muscle fibre</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are differences between Type I and Type II muscles? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: .2in; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Features</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type I (slow twitch muscle)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type II&nbsp;(fast twitch muscle)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Function</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Postural, weight bearing</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Purposeful movements</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Energy source</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">fatty acids</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Glycogen</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Mitochondria</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Many (aerobic respiration- oxidative)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Few (anaerobic respiration)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Color</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Red, more myoglobin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">White, less myoglobin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Fatigue</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Slow</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Rapid</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: #E5E5E5; border: none; padding: 0in; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[@ Type <strong><u>1</u></strong>: &lsquo;1 <strong><u>slow fat red ox&rsquo;</u></strong>: &ndash;slow twitch &ndash;lipid accumulation &ndash;red fibers &ndash;oxidative</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: #E5E5E5; border: none; padding: 0in; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type <strong><u>2</u></strong>: &lsquo;<strong><u>2 fast skinny white breasts</u></strong>&rsquo;: &ndash;fast twitch &ndash;low lipid &ndash; white fibers, like chicken breasts]</span></p>\r\n<ol start=\"27\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are Nissl Bodies? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Nissl bodies are rough endoplasmic reticulum of nerve cell. </span></p> \n<p><span>They are called as Nissl body because they are stained with Nissl stain</span></p> \n<ol> \n <li><strong><span> subchpstart::::EMBRYOLOGYsubchpend::::</span></strong></li> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>When are the 2 layer and 3 layer embryos formed? ",
    "answer": " </strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>2-layer embryo in 2<sup>nd</sup> week&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>3-layer embryo in 3<sup>rd</sup> week</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span>[@ 2 week – 2 layer, 3 weeks – 3 layer, 4 weeks – 4 limbs appear] </span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Somites develop from ......... mesoderm. [PGI 99] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Paraxial B) Lateral plate&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Extraembryonic&nbsp; D) Intermediate&nbsp; </span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: A) Paraxial</span></strong></p> \n<p><span><br></span> <span><br></span></p> \n<p><span>During the course of development, the paraxial mesoderm becomes segmented into cubical masses which are known as somites or metamere or primitive segments.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Muscular component of dorsal aorta develops from: [AI 11] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Intermediate mesoderm</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Axial mesoderm</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Lateral plate mesoderm</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Paraxial mesoderm</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Paraxial mesoderm</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Paraxial mesoderm &gt; Lateral plate mesoderm<br>Vascular smooth muscle cells are traditionally believed to arise from splanchnic layer of lateral plate mesoderm. But recent studies have demonstrated that smooth muscle cells of dorsal aorta are actually derived from&nbsp;<strong>paraxial somatic mesoderm</strong>.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are primordial germ cells? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>The primordial germ cells origin from the wall of yolk sac that is endodermal. They&nbsp;migrate into the gonadal portion of urogenital ridge. So, all the components are mesodermal in origin but the germ cells are endodermal in origin.</span></p> \n<p><span>Genital and urological structures develop from urogenital ridge located in the posterior wall of embryo abdomen. </span></p> \n<p><span>Role of primordial germ cells – As the germ cells reach the gonadal portion of urogenital ridge, they form gamete in the future. They induce the mesoderm to develop into the gonad. &nbsp;Thus, although the mesodermal cells are destined to develop into gonad, they cannot differentiate into gonad if not induced by primordial germ cells.&nbsp;</span></p> \n<p><span>In the Y chromosome, there is SRY (Sex determining Region of Y) gene,&nbsp;and this gene codes for Testis Determining Factor (TDF). In the presence of TDF, that gonad becomes the testis, and in absence of TDF, it becomes the ovary. In other words, the embryo is preprogrammed to become a female, and if there is no stimulus, it will become female.&nbsp;A female is not female because she has XX chromosome, she is female because she does not have Y chromosome.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the factors that make male organs in a preprogrammed female gonad? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 18.9pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 99.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"132\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Testis determining factor</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 125.35pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"167\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">From SRY gene of y chromosome makes testis.&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 99.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"132\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Testosterone secreted from Leydig cells</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 125.35pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"167\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Forms duct system of male reproductive system.</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 99.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"132\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Mullerian Inhibiting factor (MIF) from Sertoli cells</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 125.35pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"167\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">That inhibits the mullerian tract.</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ul>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">The inhibition is compulsory. If there is no inhibition, the preprogrammed embryo forms all female organs.&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">In absence of SRY gene, there is no production of TDF. Testis does not develop and there is no production of testosterone to produce male organs. There are no&nbsp;Sertoli cells to produce MIF, female organs develop as preprogrammed.&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n</ul>\r\n<ol start=\"6\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Development of testes is dependent upon which of the following? [MANIPAL 02] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) X chromosome</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Y chromosome</span></li> \n<li><span>C) XY chromosome</span></li> \n<li><span>D) XX chromosome</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: B) Y chromosome</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>The gene that regulates normal morphogenesis during development is: [AIIMS 02] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) PTEN</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Homeobox</span></li> \n<li><span>C) P-16</span></li> \n<li><span>D) FMR-1 GENE</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: B) Homeobox</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Researchers believe that the development of an embryo is greatly influenced by so called homeotic genes, which interact with networks of other genes to determine the position of various body parts.</span></p> \n<p><span>Homeotic genes contain sequences called&nbsp;<strong>homeo-boxes</strong>, which can be found in organisms ranging from sea urchins to humans.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What Hormones are required to form female organs and male organs? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which phase of intrauterine life has the highest risk of teratogenicity? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The fetus has the highest risk of teratogenicity in post conception age of 3-8 weeks. Before this time (&lt;2 weeks), the fetus is either intact or dead. After this period (9<sup>+</sup>weeks), there is either hypertrophy or hyperplasia.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is embryonal period and fetal period? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Embryonal period – 3-8 weeks [KU 13]</span></li> \n <li><span>Fetal period – 8weeks to child birth</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which cell in the body is tetraploid? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Primary spermatocyte or oocyte is tetraploid.</span></li> \n <li><span>After DNA replication, DNA amount is doubled to form tetraploid cells.</span></li> \n <li><span>Though there are still 46 chromosomes, each chromosome has twice much DNA after DNA replication, so the cell is tetraploid.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How many sperm and ovum does the primary spermatocyte and primary oocyte give? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>One Primary oocyte gives one ovum. There is unequal first meiotic cell division of primary oocyte. One cell receives almost all cytoplasm, and the other cell thus converts into first polar body, same for secondary oocyte. Thus, only one ovum is produced. One Primary spermatocyte gives 4 sperms.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the difference in mitosis division in other somatic cells and Zygote? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>In somatic cells, there is cell growth in between the cell division. When a cell divides, it results in half the size of mother cell. The daughter cell grows to a definite size before it again divides.</span></li> \n <li><span>In zygote, there is no growth of the daughter cells. There is only the division of the cell. So, when a zygote divides into two cells, each cell is half the size of zygote, and when these cells further divide, to form 4 and 8 cells, the size of the resulting cells become 1/4<sup>th</sup> and 1/8<sup>th</sup> the size of the zygote. Thus there is no increase in volume. <strong>The zygote and morula are of same size</strong>. This type of cell division is also called as Cleavage division. As the cleavage proceeds, a solid mass of&nbsp;<strong><u>sixteen cell</u></strong>[UP 94] is formed. This is called Morula.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is blastocyst? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Blastocyst consists of an outer layer or trophoblast and inner layer of embryoblast. The enclosed cavity is blastocele.</span></li> \n <li><strong><u><span>Blastocyst</span></u></strong><strong><span>is the stage of implantation in the endometrium of uterus</span></strong><span> [AI 94] consisting of two cell groups.</span> \n  <ol> \n   <li><span>Embryoblast</span></li> \n   <li><span>Trophoblast</span></li> \n  </ol> </li> \n</ul>   \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the types of trophoblast? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Cytotrophoblast</span></p> \n<p><span>Syncytiotrophoblast </span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cells of cytotrophoblast are metabolically active and divide rapidly; the divided cells fuse and form syncytiotrophoblast.</span></li> \n <li><span>Syncytiotrophoblast cause erosion of uterus for implantation and produce hCG hormone. </span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>When does uteroplacental circulation begin? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>On day 11-12</span></strong><span>, [IOM 11, KU 13] primitive uteroplacental circulation forms with oxygenated maternal blood arriving via spiral arterioles, seeping into the lacunae and leaving via endometrial venous capillaries.</span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the events in second week of embryo? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Formation of early placenta</span></p> \n<p><span>Formation of double layered embryo</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Epiblast – give future embryo</span></li> \n <li><span>Hypoblast – degenerate</span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>The cell layers between epiblast and hypoblast are separable except at a point called as prechordal plate. It is the site of future mouth. It determines the polarity of the circular disc of cells that has no polarity. By determining the head end, we can now determine the left, right, head and tail end of embryo.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is primitive groove or streak? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Towards the tail end of epiblast forms a groove in the midline, called primitive streak. Here, the cells of the epiblast from left and right migrates to the midline and goes beneath to the hypoblast.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How are endoderm, mesoderm, and ectoderm formed? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The cells from the epiblast migrate down through the primitive streak to the site of hypoblast. The cells of hypoblast degenerate and are replaced by the migrated cells to form endoderm.</span></li> \n <li><span>The cells of epiblast that migrate and remain in the position between epiblast and hypoblast form middle layer. The cells that migrate either in left or right side to form mesoderm.</span></li> \n <li><span>The remaining cells in epiblast form ectoderm.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How is Notochord formed? ",
    "answer": " </strong>  \n<ul> \n <li><span>The cells from the epiblast that migrate through primitive streak and remain between epiblast and hypoblast in the left and right form middle layer. The cells at the site of middle layer that remain in the midline form Notochord.&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Notochord gives Nucleus pulposus of intervertebral disc. </span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the sub-divisions of ectoderm? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Neuroectoderm – occupy midline</span></li> \n <li><span>Neural crest ectoderm – occupy side of neuroectoderm cells</span></li> \n <li><span>Surface ectoderm</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is gastroschisis? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Defect in fusion of the lateral body folds results in gastroschisis – abdominal viscera exit through a defect in the abdominal wall and are in the amniotic cavity.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which of these appears first? [IOM 09] ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">A) Pharyngeal arch</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">B) Lower limb bud&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">C) Upper limb bud&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">D) Neural plate</span></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: right; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ans: D) Neural plate</span></strong></p>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">1 week</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Fertilized oocyte, Pronucleus</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">2 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Implantation</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">3 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Gastrulation, notochordal process</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">4 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Somite number 4-12, neural fold fuses&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">5 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Somite number 30, leg buds, lens placode, pharyngeal arches,&nbsp;<strong>ossification of clavicle starts.</strong>&nbsp;[IOM 08]&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">6 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Foot plate&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">7 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ossification commences&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">8 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Upper limbs longer and bent at elbow.</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 20.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: Wingdings;\">&micro;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 40.0pt 0in 20.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "TISSUES"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How do Prokaryotic cell differ from eukaryotic cell? [AI 99] ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Nucleus</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>Devoid of nuclear membrane</span></strong><span>and nucleolus&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>No deoxyribonucleoproteins i.e. their nucleic DNA is not associated with basic protein (histone).&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>The genome consists of a single molecule double stranded DNA arranged in the form of a circle.</span></li> \n <li><span>Mitotic division does not occur and these divide by binary fission.</span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>Cytoplasm&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>No protoplasmic streaming&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Absence of endoplasmic reticulum Mitochondria, lysosomes and golgi apparatus.&nbsp;</span></strong></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>Chemical composition&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cell wall of prokaryotes contain Muramic acid and peptidoglycan (no sterols) while cell wall of eukaryotes contains sterols.</span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the composition of cell membrane? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>The plasma membrane is about 40% lipid and&nbsp;<strong><u>60%</u>&nbsp;protein</strong>, [AIIMS 94] but these proportions vary greatly. Most of the lipids in the plasma membrane are phospholipids.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the intracellular organelles that have double membrane. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Nucleus&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Endoplasmic membrane&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Mitochondria</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which cell organelle has extrachromosomal DNA? [IOM 08] ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Mitochondria</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are heterochromatin and euchromatin? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Heterochromatin – highly condensed chromatin fibres that are transcriptionally inactive, 10% chromatin is heterochromatin. &nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Euchromatin – more extended form of DNA that is&nbsp;<strong>transcriptionally active</strong>, [IOM 09] 90% chromatin is euchromatin.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the main function of the nucleolus? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>It is responsible for rRNA synthesis by assembling the ribosomes</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the cells that have more than one nucleus. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Hepatocytes –binucleate&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Osteoclasts - &nbsp;multinucleate&nbsp;</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are polysomes? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Polyribosomes (or polysomes) are a cluster of ribosomes, bound to a mRNA molecule. &nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Many ribosomes read one mRNA simultaneously, progressing along the mRNA to synthesize the same protein.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Circulatory system in a cell is name for: [IOM 08] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) RER</span></li> \n<li><span>B) SER&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Golgi apparatus&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Polyribosome</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: A) RER</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>The transport system of a cell is comprised of: [KU 13] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ol> \n <li><span>Endoplasmic reticulum</span></li> \n <li><span>Ribosome</span></li> \n <li><span>Nucleus</span></li> \n <li><span>Mitochondria</span></li> \n</ol>   \n<p><strong><span>Ans: A) Endoplasmic reticulum</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the functions of Smooth endoplasmic reticulum? [BPKIHS 08] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>Steroid Hormones synthesis</span></strong><span>[UP 95]&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Hydroxylation reactions&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Conjugation reaction&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Glycogen metabolism&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>In striated muscles, for storage of calcium ions, as sarcoplasmic reticulum.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the function of Golgi apparatus? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The proteins that are synthesized by rough endoplasmic reticulum must next be sent to the Golgi apparatus. [BPKIHS 12]</span></li> \n <li><span>Newly synthesized proteins enter into the Cis-Golgi, <strong><u>sorting</u>and the glycosylation of proteins</strong>&nbsp;[AI 08,14] occur in medial golgi and Packaging occurs in Trans-golgi for secretion as secretory vesicles. &nbsp;</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span><br></span> <span><br></span></p> \n<p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which of the following is the marker of Golgi apparatus? [AI 95, IOM 11] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Pyruvate kinase&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Adenylate cyclase&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Sodium potassium ATPase</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Galactosyl transferase&nbsp;</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Galactosyl transferase</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Galactosyl transferase is a type of glycosyltransferase which catalyzes the transfer of galactose. It occurs in golgi apparatus as a part of post-translational modification.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is Hyperproinsulinemia? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Elevated level of proinsulin in the serum resulting from failure of a peptidase to cleave proinsulin and C-peptide in the Golgi apparatus, resulting in NIDDM.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How are lysosomes produced? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>The synthesis of lysosomal hydrolase occurs in the RER, the hydrolases are transferred to the Golgi apparatus, where they are modified and packaged into lysosomes.</span></p> \n<p><span>They are produced by budding from the trans side of golgi apparatus.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are peroxisomes? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>They are specialized type of lysosomes in a way that they contain various enzymes involved in various stages of degradation.</span></li> \n <li><span>The major product they degrade is hydrogen peroxide and the major enzyme thus is catalase.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the functions of peroxisomes. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Degradation of hydrogen peroxide</span></li> \n <li><span>Beta-oxidation of very long fatty acids</span></li> \n <li><span>Bile acid and cholesterol synthesis</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is Zellweger syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Zellweger syndrome, also called cerebrohepatorenal syndrome, is a rare congenital disorder, characterized by the reduction or absence of functional peroxisomes in the cells of an individual.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are the enzymes required for electron transport system located in mitochondria? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>In the <strong>infolding of inner membrane of mitochondria called as cristae</strong>. [BPKIHS08]<strong> ",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name cytoskeletal elements. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Microfilaments - smallest</span></li> \n <li><span>Intermediate filaments</span></li> \n <li><span>Microtubules – largest</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the function of microfilaments? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cellular motility for cells like WBC</span></li> \n <li><span>Form contractile ring in cytokinesis</span></li> \n <li><span>Form core of microvilli and thus increase the absorption area of epithelial cells.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name intermediate filaments. ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Keratin&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; –&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Desmin</span></p> \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Vimentin&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Peripherin</span></p> \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Internexin&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Neurofilament</span></p> \n<p><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Lamins&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>–&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>Nestin</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Functions of microtubules are: ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Intracellular transport of vesicles</span></li> \n <li><span>In cilia and flagella -&nbsp;<strong>responsible for shape and motility of the cell</strong>. [AI 95]&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Microtubules form mitotic spindles.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Cell motility is due to: [AIIMS 96] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Fibrin B)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Phorin</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Tubulin D)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Flagellin</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: C) Tubulin</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Tubulin is a protein present in microtubules of cells and responsible for cell motility.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are stereocilia? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>They are apical modification of cell; closely related to cilia or microvilli.</span></li> \n <li><span>But they are taller and branched unlike microvilli and do not have the motility like cilia.</span></li> \n <li><span>Some consider them specialized microvilli.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are stereocilia found? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Branched – epididymis</span></li> \n <li><span>Unbranched – hair cells in inner ear</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong> What is the ATP splitting enzyme in cilia? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Dynein is a very large&nbsp;<strong>force generating protein</strong>&nbsp;[AI 01] that has a molecular configuration similar to arms. Contraction of these arms facilitates the movement of cilia and flagella of bacteria.</span></p> \n<p><span>Kinesin also has similar activity.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong> Name disease conditions due to accumulation of intermediate filaments. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Alzheimer’s disease</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Mallory bodies</span></strong><span>in Alcoholic hepatitis. [UP 93, AP 94]</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Name the drugs that prevent formation of mitotic spindle. ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Vinblastine and Vincristine – thus used in cancer therapy</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the components of basement membrane? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Collagen type IV</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Laminin</span></strong><span>[AI 92, 95]&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Fibronectin&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Entactin&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Proteoglycans</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is difference between basement membrane and basal lamina? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The basement membrane is the fusion of two lamina, the basal lamina and the reticular lamina (or lamina reticularis).</span></li> \n <li><span>The basal lamina is a layer of extracellular matrix secreted by the epithelial cells, on which the epithelium sits and a reticular lamina secreted by other cells.</span></li> \n <li><span>The term \"basal lamina\" is usually used with electron microscopy, while the term \"basement membrane\" is usually used with light microscopy.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are desmosomes and hemidesmosomes? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>A desmosome (desmos, band or dense, soma, body), also known as macula adherens (plural</span></strong><span>: maculae adherentes) is a cell structure for cell-to-cell adhesion.</span></li> \n <li><span>Desmosomes help to resist shearing forces and are found in simple and stratified squamous epithelium.</span></li> \n <li><span>Hemidesmosome are half of desmosome and help to bind the epithelial cell with the basement membrane of the cell.&nbsp;</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are cadherins? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cadherins are calcium dependent adhesion proteins that ensure the adhesion of cells within the tissues.</span></li> \n <li><span>First step of invasion of malignant cells through an epithelium results from a loss of expression of cadherins that weakens the epithelium.</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span>[@<strong><u>Ca</u></strong> <strong><u>d</u></strong> <strong><u>herins</u></strong> - <strong><u>Ca</u></strong> <strong><u>d</u></strong>ependent ad<strong><u>herin</u></strong> molecule]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Catabolism of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is carried out by [IOM 10] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Lysosomes</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Mitochondria</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Endoplasmic reticulum&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Peroxisomes</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Peroxisomes</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n <li><strong><span> subchpstart::::TISSUESsubchpend::::</span></strong></li> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are stratified cuboidal epithelium found? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Duct of salivary gland and sweat gland. It is the only place where we find the stratified cuboidal epithelium.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where&nbsp;are transitional epithelium found? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Transitional epithelium occurs in ureters, urinary bladder and&nbsp;<strong>proximal (prostatic) urethra</strong>. [IOM 10]</span></li> \n <li><span>Within the cytoplasm are fusiform vesicles lined by unit membranes, the inner lamellae of are similarly thickened.</span></li> \n <li><span>These vesicles are probably formed by infolding of the plasma membrane, and their walls constitute<strong>reserve material</strong>&nbsp;[AI 03] used in rapid expansion of the cells.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the composition of extracellular matrix? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Gel part contain proteoglycan (heparin sulphate +&nbsp;chondroitin sulphate)&nbsp;and glycoprotein. <strong>The major macromolecules primarily found in extracellular matrix are <u></u> </strong>[AI 14]</span></li> \n <li><span>Fibrillar protein contains collagen, elastin, Fibrillin (elastin + Fibrillin =elastic fibres) and fibronectin.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>All are glycoproteins except: [IOM 10] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) hCG&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Immunoglobulins&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) ALP</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Albumin</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Albumin</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is collagen? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Collagen is the major macromolecule of connective tissue and is the most common protein in the animal world.</span></li> \n <li><span>The most important property of collagen molecule is&nbsp;<strong>triple helix structure</strong>[AIIMS 95, UP 99] made of three polypeptide subunits.</span></li> \n <li><span>Collagen consists of&nbsp;<strong>glycine, <u>proline</u></strong> and 4-hydroxyproline. [UP 00]</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the steps in synthesis of collagen? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Collagen precursors are produced in rough endoplasmic reticulum of fibroblasts </span><span>?</span><span> hydroxylation that requires vitamin C and glycosylation in golgi apparatus </span><span>?</span><span> triple helix formation&nbsp;in golgi apparatus </span><span>?</span><span> released from golgi as procollagen </span><span>?</span><span> propeptides are removed forming tropocollagen </span><span>?</span><span> tropocollagen are assembled to form collagen fibre.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the defect in Ehlers Danlos syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Conversion of procollagen to tropocollagen is defective.</span></li> \n <li><span>Forms fragile skin, hyperextensible joints, varicose veins.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the types of collagen? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Collagen</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Features</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type I</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Strongest; Present in strong tissues like b<strong><u>ONE</u></strong>s, ligaments, tendon, skin, sclera, teeth, mature scar </span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type II</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Weaker; Present in <strong>cartilages</strong></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\"> (car<strong><u>TWO</u></strong>lage), [IOM 02] intervertebral disc</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type III</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Much weaker; Present in Blood vessels, forms reticular fibres in various organs; Stained with PAS and silver salts&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 49.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"66\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type IV</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 191.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"255\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Weakest of all collagens</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Supports only a row of epithelial cells as in<strong> basement membrane </strong></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[IOM 09]</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 115%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[Note: Collagenase (metalloenzyme containing zinc) breaks type III collagen in granulation tissue to replace by type I collagen(stronger)]</span></p>\r\n<ol start=\"9\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 115%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 115%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which enzyme mediates the degradation of basement membrane? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Basement membrane consists of network of amorphous non-fibrillar collagen (mostly type IV).</span></p> \n<p><strong><span>Matrix metalloproteinases</span></strong><span>&nbsp;[AI 07] is a family of enzymes that are involved in degradation of basement membrane.</span></p> \n<p><span>[Note: Type IV collagenase is present in neutrophil and malignant cell - so have similar mechanism of invading the basement membrane for chemotaxis and metastases respectively]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which collagen is defective in Alport syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Type IV collagen</span></p> \n<p><span>Alport syndrome is due to mutation of COL4A3, COL4A4, COL4A5 gene involved in collagen biosynthesis, which leads to poor&nbsp;type IV collagen&nbsp;network, which is an important structural component of basement membranes in the&nbsp;kidney, inner&nbsp;ear and&nbsp;eye.</span></p> \n<p><span>It causes glomerulonephritis, hearing loss, cataract, keratoconus, lenticonus, etc.</span></p> \n<p><span>[<strong><u>@ Alports syndrome</u> -<u> &nbsp;Al-four-t’s Syndrome - type IV</u></strong>]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Where are elastic fibres located? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>These fibres provide elasticity or resilience to the tissues meaning that they will return to their resting length after stretch.</span></li> \n <li><span>They are present in lungs, blood vessels especially arteries and dermis of the skin. </span></li> \n <li><span>Elastin + Fibrillin =elastin fibres</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the defect in Marfan syndrome? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Marfan’s Syndrome is associated with a gene defect in <strong>Fibrillin-1 protein</strong> [AI 14] located in chromosome 15, that causes significant weakening in elastic tissue. </span></p> \n<p><span>[@<strong>M</strong>ar<strong>F</strong>a<strong>N</strong>&nbsp;=&nbsp;<strong>M</strong>utation&nbsp;<strong>F</strong>ibrilli<strong>N</strong>,&nbsp;<strong>F</strong>iftee<strong>N</strong>]</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the features of Marfan's syndrome? [AI 94, AIIMS 95] ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"321\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Musculoskeletal signs and conditions -&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Long, thin extremities (arachnodactyly)</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Tall body habitus&nbsp;</span></strong></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Pectus deformity&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">High arched palate</span></strong></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Hyperextensible joints and ligaments</span></strong></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"321\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ocular signs and conditions -&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Reduced vision as the result of&nbsp;<strong>subluxation of lens (ectopic lentis) </strong>[AI 93]&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Myopia&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Glaucoma&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Retinal detachment</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"321\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Cardiovascular signs and conditions&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Aortic aneurysm that typically begin at the&nbsp;<strong><u>base of aorta</u></strong>&nbsp;[AI 95]&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Aortic regurgitation&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Mitral valve prolapse&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 104%; background: white; margin: 1.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Courier New';\">o<span style=\"font: 7.0pt 'Times New Roman';\">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 104%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">SABE</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr style=\"height: 36.4pt;\">\r\n<td style=\"width: 241.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt; height: 36.4pt;\" width=\"321\">&nbsp;</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ol start=\"15\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Normal metacarpal index is: ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) &gt;10.4 B) 5.4-7.9</span></li> \n<li><span>C) &gt;5.4 D) 8.4-10.4</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: B) 5.4-7.9</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Metacarpal index(MCI) is determined by dividing the length of each of the last four metacarpals by the width of its midpoint and averaging the values.</span></p> \n<p><strong><span>Normal MCI &lt;8</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Those with Marfan's syndrome have MCI &gt;8.4</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are examples of Glycosaminoglycan? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Glycosaminoglycan contains two glucose molecules (disaccharide) along with amino group, thus the name glycosaminoglycan.</span></p> \n<p><span>GAG is either sulphated or non-sulphated.</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>Sulphated GAG</span></strong><span>: Chondroitin sulphate, Heparin sulphate, Dermatan sulphate and Keratin sulphate</span></li> \n <li><strong><span>Non sulphated include</span></strong><span>: Hyaluronic acid</span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>Presence of sulphate makes the GAG negatively charged and thus repels negatively charged particles.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are Hyaluronic acids? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Hyaluronic acids are <strong>non-sulphated</strong> GAGs that form extracellular matrix.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are proteoglycans? &nbsp;[AI 07] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Proteoglycans are macromolecules in which a core<strong>protein is attached covalently to one or more glycosaminoglycan chains (complex carbohydrate</strong>).</span></li> \n <li><span>They are sulphated GAGs.</span></li> \n <li><span>They are <strong>chondroitin sulphate</strong>, heparin sulphate, dermatan sulphate and keratin sulphate.</span></li> \n <li><span>Proteoglycans&nbsp;<strong>hold&nbsp;<u>large</u>amount of water and occupy space</strong>. They are&nbsp;<strong>negatively charged</strong>.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Why are proteins not filtered in Glomerulosa? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Proteins are negatively charged and the basement membranes of podocytes contain heparin sulphate that is negatively charged and thus they repel protein.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the types of cartilages? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: .2in; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: .75in; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"72\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Hyaline</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">cartilage</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 178.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"237\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Contains maximum amount of glycosaminoglycan. </span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Location - Articular surface of synovial joints, cartilage of nose, larynx, trachea, bronchi</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: .75in; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"72\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Elastic</span></strong></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">cartilage</span></strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 178.0pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"237\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Contains maximum elastic fibers</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Location - External ear, <strong>epiglottis</strong> [UP 95, 98]</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[@<strong><u><span style=\"background: #CCCCCC;\">E</span></u></strong><span style=\"background: #CCCCCC;\">lastic cartilage: Ext.&nbsp;<strong><u>e</u></strong>ar, <strong><u>E</u></strong>piglottis]</span>&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: .75in; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"72\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Fibro-</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">cartilage</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 178.0pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"237\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Lacks perichondrium</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">This is the only cartilage that has type I collagen. Presence of type I collagen gives cartilage greater resistance being stretched.</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Location - intervertebral disc, menisci of knee</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ol start=\"21\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are hard and soft keratin? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 45.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"60\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Hard </span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">keratin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 196.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"261\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">These keratins are less pliable than soft keratins as&nbsp;<strong>they contain more disulfide bonds</strong>. [AI 12] E.g. hair, horn,&nbsp;<strong>nail&nbsp;</strong></span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 45.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"60\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Soft </span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">keratin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 196.0pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"261\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">These keratins are more pliable than hard keratins as they contain less number of disulfide bonds. E.g.&nbsp;<strong>skin</strong>&nbsp;(and callus).</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ol start=\"22\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are labile cells? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Labile cells are the cells that continue to proliferate throughout the life, replacing the cells that are continually being destroyed. Labile cells in body are&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cells of splenic, lymphoid and hematopoietic tissue&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Cells of surface epithelium such as stratified squamous surfaces of skin, oral cavity, cervix, vagina</span></li> \n <li><span>Lining mucosa of all the excretory ducts of glands of the body such as salivary glands, pancreas, and biliary tract</span></li> \n <li><span>The columnar epithelium of GI tract, uterus, fallopian tube and transitional epithelium of the urinary tract</span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which of the following cells are not labile? [AI 93, IOM 00] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Intestinal cells&nbsp; B) Keratinocytes&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Kupffer cells&nbsp; D) Hepatocytes</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Hepatocytes</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>The cells of liver, pancreas, kidney are [NAMS12] ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -24.55pt; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: 120.5pt 141.75pt; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 42.55pt;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">A) Stable cells B) &nbsp;&nbsp; Permanent cells</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -24.55pt; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: 120.5pt 141.75pt; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 42.55pt;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">C) Labile cells D)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; None &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: right; text-indent: -24.55pt; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: 120.5pt 141.75pt; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 42.55pt;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ans: A) Stable cells </span></strong></p>\r\n<ol start=\"25\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 112%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 112%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Define epimysium, perimysium and endomysium. ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Epi – connective tissue that surrounds entire muscle</span></li> \n <li><span>Peri – connective tissue that surrounds bundle of muscle fibres</span></li> \n <li><span>Endo – connective tissue that surrounds each muscle fibre</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are differences between Type I and Type II muscles? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: .2in; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Features</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type I (slow twitch muscle)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type II&nbsp;(fast twitch muscle)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Function</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Postural, weight bearing</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Purposeful movements</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Energy source</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">fatty acids</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Glycogen</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Mitochondria</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Many (aerobic respiration- oxidative)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Few (anaerobic respiration)</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Color</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Red, more myoglobin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">White, less myoglobin</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 66.6pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"89\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Fatigue</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 86.45pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"115\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Slow</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 75.8pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"101\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Rapid</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: #E5E5E5; border: none; padding: 0in; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">[@ Type <strong><u>1</u></strong>: &lsquo;1 <strong><u>slow fat red ox&rsquo;</u></strong>: &ndash;slow twitch &ndash;lipid accumulation &ndash;red fibers &ndash;oxidative</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; background: #E5E5E5; border: none; padding: 0in; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Type <strong><u>2</u></strong>: &lsquo;<strong><u>2 fast skinny white breasts</u></strong>&rsquo;: &ndash;fast twitch &ndash;low lipid &ndash; white fibers, like chicken breasts]</span></p>\r\n<ol start=\"27\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 110%; tab-stops: list .25in; background: white; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are Nissl Bodies? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Nissl bodies are rough endoplasmic reticulum of nerve cell. </span></p> \n<p><span>They are called as Nissl body because they are stained with Nissl stain</span></p> \n<ol> \n <li><strong><span> subchpstart::::EMBRYOLOGYsubchpend::::</span></strong></li> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>When are the 2 layer and 3 layer embryos formed? ",
    "answer": " </strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>2-layer embryo in 2<sup>nd</sup> week&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>3-layer embryo in 3<sup>rd</sup> week</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span>[@ 2 week – 2 layer, 3 weeks – 3 layer, 4 weeks – 4 limbs appear] </span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Somites develop from ......... mesoderm. [PGI 99] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Paraxial B) Lateral plate&nbsp;</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Extraembryonic&nbsp; D) Intermediate&nbsp; </span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: A) Paraxial</span></strong></p> \n<p><span><br></span> <span><br></span></p> \n<p><span>During the course of development, the paraxial mesoderm becomes segmented into cubical masses which are known as somites or metamere or primitive segments.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Muscular component of dorsal aorta develops from: [AI 11] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) Intermediate mesoderm</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Axial mesoderm</span></li> \n<li><span>C) Lateral plate mesoderm</span></li> \n<li><span>D) Paraxial mesoderm</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: D) Paraxial mesoderm</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Paraxial mesoderm &gt; Lateral plate mesoderm<br>Vascular smooth muscle cells are traditionally believed to arise from splanchnic layer of lateral plate mesoderm. But recent studies have demonstrated that smooth muscle cells of dorsal aorta are actually derived from&nbsp;<strong>paraxial somatic mesoderm</strong>.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are primordial germ cells? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>The primordial germ cells origin from the wall of yolk sac that is endodermal. They&nbsp;migrate into the gonadal portion of urogenital ridge. So, all the components are mesodermal in origin but the germ cells are endodermal in origin.</span></p> \n<p><span>Genital and urological structures develop from urogenital ridge located in the posterior wall of embryo abdomen. </span></p> \n<p><span>Role of primordial germ cells – As the germ cells reach the gonadal portion of urogenital ridge, they form gamete in the future. They induce the mesoderm to develop into the gonad. &nbsp;Thus, although the mesodermal cells are destined to develop into gonad, they cannot differentiate into gonad if not induced by primordial germ cells.&nbsp;</span></p> \n<p><span>In the Y chromosome, there is SRY (Sex determining Region of Y) gene,&nbsp;and this gene codes for Testis Determining Factor (TDF). In the presence of TDF, that gonad becomes the testis, and in absence of TDF, it becomes the ovary. In other words, the embryo is preprogrammed to become a female, and if there is no stimulus, it will become female.&nbsp;A female is not female because she has XX chromosome, she is female because she does not have Y chromosome.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the factors that make male organs in a preprogrammed female gonad? ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 18.9pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 99.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"132\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Testis determining factor</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 125.35pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"167\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">From SRY gene of y chromosome makes testis.&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 99.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"132\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Testosterone secreted from Leydig cells</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 125.35pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"167\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Forms duct system of male reproductive system.</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 99.0pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"132\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Mullerian Inhibiting factor (MIF) from Sertoli cells</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 125.35pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"167\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">That inhibits the mullerian tract.</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<ul>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">The inhibition is compulsory. If there is no inhibition, the preprogrammed embryo forms all female organs.&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">In absence of SRY gene, there is no production of TDF. Testis does not develop and there is no production of testosterone to produce male organs. There are no&nbsp;Sertoli cells to produce MIF, female organs develop as preprogrammed.&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n</ul>\r\n<ol start=\"6\">\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; text-indent: -.25in; line-height: 117%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 117%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Development of testes is dependent upon which of the following? [MANIPAL 02] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) X chromosome</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Y chromosome</span></li> \n<li><span>C) XY chromosome</span></li> \n<li><span>D) XX chromosome</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: B) Y chromosome</span></strong></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>The gene that regulates normal morphogenesis during development is: [AIIMS 02] ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<li><span>A) PTEN</span></li> \n<li><span>B) Homeobox</span></li> \n<li><span>C) P-16</span></li> \n<li><span>D) FMR-1 GENE</span></li>  \n<p><strong><span>Ans: B) Homeobox</span></strong></p> \n<p><span>Researchers believe that the development of an embryo is greatly influenced by so called homeotic genes, which interact with networks of other genes to determine the position of various body parts.</span></p> \n<p><span>Homeotic genes contain sequences called&nbsp;<strong>homeo-boxes</strong>, which can be found in organisms ranging from sea urchins to humans.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What Hormones are required to form female organs and male organs? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which phase of intrauterine life has the highest risk of teratogenicity? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The fetus has the highest risk of teratogenicity in post conception age of 3-8 weeks. Before this time (&lt;2 weeks), the fetus is either intact or dead. After this period (9<sup>+</sup>weeks), there is either hypertrophy or hyperplasia.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is embryonal period and fetal period? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Embryonal period – 3-8 weeks [KU 13]</span></li> \n <li><span>Fetal period – 8weeks to child birth</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which cell in the body is tetraploid? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Primary spermatocyte or oocyte is tetraploid.</span></li> \n <li><span>After DNA replication, DNA amount is doubled to form tetraploid cells.</span></li> \n <li><span>Though there are still 46 chromosomes, each chromosome has twice much DNA after DNA replication, so the cell is tetraploid.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How many sperm and ovum does the primary spermatocyte and primary oocyte give? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>One Primary oocyte gives one ovum. There is unequal first meiotic cell division of primary oocyte. One cell receives almost all cytoplasm, and the other cell thus converts into first polar body, same for secondary oocyte. Thus, only one ovum is produced. One Primary spermatocyte gives 4 sperms.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is the difference in mitosis division in other somatic cells and Zygote? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>In somatic cells, there is cell growth in between the cell division. When a cell divides, it results in half the size of mother cell. The daughter cell grows to a definite size before it again divides.</span></li> \n <li><span>In zygote, there is no growth of the daughter cells. There is only the division of the cell. So, when a zygote divides into two cells, each cell is half the size of zygote, and when these cells further divide, to form 4 and 8 cells, the size of the resulting cells become 1/4<sup>th</sup> and 1/8<sup>th</sup> the size of the zygote. Thus there is no increase in volume. <strong>The zygote and morula are of same size</strong>. This type of cell division is also called as Cleavage division. As the cleavage proceeds, a solid mass of&nbsp;<strong><u>sixteen cell</u></strong>[UP 94] is formed. This is called Morula.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is blastocyst? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Blastocyst consists of an outer layer or trophoblast and inner layer of embryoblast. The enclosed cavity is blastocele.</span></li> \n <li><strong><u><span>Blastocyst</span></u></strong><strong><span>is the stage of implantation in the endometrium of uterus</span></strong><span> [AI 94] consisting of two cell groups.</span> \n  <ol> \n   <li><span>Embryoblast</span></li> \n   <li><span>Trophoblast</span></li> \n  </ol> </li> \n</ul>   \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the types of trophoblast? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Cytotrophoblast</span></p> \n<p><span>Syncytiotrophoblast </span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Cells of cytotrophoblast are metabolically active and divide rapidly; the divided cells fuse and form syncytiotrophoblast.</span></li> \n <li><span>Syncytiotrophoblast cause erosion of uterus for implantation and produce hCG hormone. </span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>When does uteroplacental circulation begin? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<ul> \n <li><strong><span>On day 11-12</span></strong><span>, [IOM 11, KU 13] primitive uteroplacental circulation forms with oxygenated maternal blood arriving via spiral arterioles, seeping into the lacunae and leaving via endometrial venous capillaries.</span></li> \n</ul> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the events in second week of embryo? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Formation of early placenta</span></p> \n<p><span>Formation of double layered embryo</span></p> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Epiblast – give future embryo</span></li> \n <li><span>Hypoblast – degenerate</span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>The cell layers between epiblast and hypoblast are separable except at a point called as prechordal plate. It is the site of future mouth. It determines the polarity of the circular disc of cells that has no polarity. By determining the head end, we can now determine the left, right, head and tail end of embryo.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is primitive groove or streak? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Towards the tail end of epiblast forms a groove in the midline, called primitive streak. Here, the cells of the epiblast from left and right migrates to the midline and goes beneath to the hypoblast.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How are endoderm, mesoderm, and ectoderm formed? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>The cells from the epiblast migrate down through the primitive streak to the site of hypoblast. The cells of hypoblast degenerate and are replaced by the migrated cells to form endoderm.</span></li> \n <li><span>The cells of epiblast that migrate and remain in the position between epiblast and hypoblast form middle layer. The cells that migrate either in left or right side to form mesoderm.</span></li> \n <li><span>The remaining cells in epiblast form ectoderm.</span></li> \n</ul>  \n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>How is Notochord formed? ",
    "answer": " </strong>  \n<ul> \n <li><span>The cells from the epiblast that migrate through primitive streak and remain between epiblast and hypoblast in the left and right form middle layer. The cells at the site of middle layer that remain in the midline form Notochord.&nbsp;</span></li> \n <li><span>Notochord gives Nucleus pulposus of intervertebral disc. </span></li> \n</ul> \n<p><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What are the sub-divisions of ectoderm? ",
    "answer": "</strong> \n<ul> \n <li><span>Neuroectoderm – occupy midline</span></li> \n <li><span>Neural crest ectoderm – occupy side of neuroectoderm cells</span></li> \n <li><span>Surface ectoderm</span></li> \n</ul>   \n<p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>What is gastroschisis? ",
    "answer": "</strong>  \n<p><span>Defect in fusion of the lateral body folds results in gastroschisis – abdominal viscera exit through a defect in the abdominal wall and are in the amniotic cavity.</span></p> \n<ol> \n \n</ol>",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  },
  {
    "question": "<strong>Which of these appears first? [IOM 09] ",
    "answer": "</span></strong></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">A) Pharyngeal arch</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">B) Lower limb bud&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">C) Upper limb bud&nbsp;</span></li>\r\n<li style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt .25in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">D) Neural plate</span></li>\r\n</ol>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: right; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><strong><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ans: D) Neural plate</span></strong></p>\r\n<table style=\"margin-left: 5.4pt; border-collapse: collapse; border: none;\">\r\n<tbody>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">1 week</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-left: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Fertilized oocyte, Pronucleus</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">2 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Implantation</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">3 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Gastrulation, notochordal process</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">4 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Somite number 4-12, neural fold fuses&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">5 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Somite number 30, leg buds, lens placode, pharyngeal arches,&nbsp;<strong>ossification of clavicle starts.</strong>&nbsp;[IOM 08]&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">6 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Foot plate&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">7 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Ossification commences&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n<tr>\r\n<td style=\"width: 58.5pt; border: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-top: none; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"78\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">8 weeks</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n<td style=\"width: 179.5pt; border-top: none; border-left: none; border-bottom: solid windowtext 1.0pt; border-right: solid windowtext 1.0pt; padding: 0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;\" width=\"239\">\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">Upper limbs longer and bent at elbow.</span></p>\r\n</td>\r\n</tr>\r\n</tbody>\r\n</table>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 20.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: Wingdings;\">&micro;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: justify; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 40.0pt 0in 20.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n<p style=\"text-align: center; line-height: 110%; margin: 2.0pt 0in 1.0pt 0in;\"><span style=\"font-size: 10.0pt; line-height: 110%; font-family: 'Tw Cen MT',sans-serif;\">&nbsp;</span></p>\r\n",
    "chaptername": "Basic Anatomy",
    "subchaptername": "EMBRYOLOGY"
  }
]